<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: ipsec.xml,v 1.12 2005/09/19 06:22:13 chris Exp $ -->
<chapter id="IPsec">
  <?dbhtml filename="ipsec.html"?>

  <title>IPsec</title>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ipsec-preface.html"?>

    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>IPsec (IP security) is a standard for providing security to IP
    protocols via encryption and/or authentication, typically employing
    both.  Its use in m0n0wall is for <glossterm linkend="gloss.VPN">
    Virtual Private Networks (VPN's)</glossterm>.
    </para>
    
    <para>There are two types of IPsec VPN capabilities in m0n0wall, site
    to site and remote access.  </para>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Site to Site VPN Explained</title>
        
        <para>Site to site VPN's connect two locations with static public
        IP addresses and allow traffic to be routed between the two
        networks.  This is most commonly used to connect an organization's
        branch offices back to its main office, so branch users can access
        network resources in the main office.  Prior to VPN's, much more
        expensive private Wide Area Network (WAN) links like frame relay,
        point to point T1 lines, etc. were commonly used for this
        functionality.  Some organizations are moving towards VPN links
        between sites to take advantage of reduced costs.  
        </para>
        
        <para>Site to site VPN's can also be used to link your home network
        to a friend's home network, to provide access to each other's network
        resources without opening holes in your firewalls.</para>
        
        <para>While site to site VPN's are a good solution in many cases,
        private WAN links also have their benefits.  IPsec adds processing
        overhead, and the Internet has far greater latency than a private
        network, so VPN connections are typically slower (while maybe not
        throughput-wise, they at least have much higher latency).  A point
        to point T1 typically has latency of around 4-8 ms, while a typical
        VPN connection will be 30-80+ ms
        depending on the number of hops on the Internet between the two
        VPN endpoints.  </para>
        
        <para>
        When deploying VPN's, you should stay with the same
        ISP for all sites if possible, or at a minimum, stay with ISP's that
        use the same backbone provider.  Geographic proximity usually has no
        relation to Internet proximity.  A server in the same city as you
        but on a different Internet-backbone provider could be as far away from
        you in Internet distance (hops) as a server on the other side of the
        continent.  This difference in Internet proximity can make the difference
        between a VPN with 30 ms latency and one with 80+ ms latency.
        </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Remote Access IPsec VPN</title>
        
        <para>m0n0wall provides two means of remote access VPN, PPTP
        and IPsec (with OpenVPN available in beta versions only for
        now).  m0n0wall's mobile IPsec functionality has some serious
        limitations that hinder its practicality for many deployments.
        m0n0wall does <emphasis>not</emphasis> support NAT-Traversal (NAT-T)
        for IPsec, which means if any of your client machines are behind NAT,
        IPsec VPN will not work.  This alone eliminates it as a possibility
        for most environments, since remote users will almost always need
        access from behind NAT.  Many home networks use a NAT router of some
        sort, as do most hot spot locations, hotel networks, etc.</para>
        
        <para>One good use of the m0n0wall IPsec client VPN capabilities is to
        secure all traffic sent by hosts on a wireless network or other untrusted
        network.  This will be described later in this chapter.  
        </para>
        
        <para>FIXME - A second limitation is the lack of any really good, free IPsec
        VPN clients for Windows.  Most of your remote users will likely be
        Windows laptop users, so this is another major hindrance.</para>
        
        <para>For most situations, PPTP is probably the best remote access
        VPN option in m0n0wall right now.  See the PPTP chapter for more
        information.
        </para>
        
    </sect2>

    <para>This chapter will go over configuring a site to site VPN link
    between two m0n0walls, and will discuss how to configure site to site
    links with third party IPsec-compliant devices.  The <link linkend="Example.VPN">
    Example VPN Configurations</link> chapter goes over, in detail, how to
    configure site to site IPsec links with some third party IPsec devices.
    If you have gotten m0n0wall working in a site to site IPsec configuration
    with some third party IPsec device, we would appreciate if you could put
    together a short write up of how you got it configured, preferably with
    screenshots where applicable.  
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ipsec-prerequisites.html"?>

    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>Before getting started, you need to take care of the following.
    </para>
    

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Your m0n0wall must be setup and working properly for your
        network environment.</para>
      </listitem>

    <listitem>
            <para>Both locations must be using non-overlapping LAN IP subnets.
            </para>
            <para>i.e.
        if both sites are using 192.168.1.0/24 on the LAN, no site to site
        VPN will work.  This is not a limitation in m0n0wall, it's basic IP
        routing.  When any host on either of your networks tries to
        communicate with 192.168.1.0/24, it will consider that host to be on
        its local LAN and the packets will never reach m0n0wall to be passed
        over the VPN connection.  Similarly, if one site is using, for example,
        192.168.0.0/16 and one using 192.168.1.0/24, these subnets are also
        overlapping and a site to site VPN will not work.  </para>
        
        <para>Keep in mind the more networks you link together the more
        important this basic fact becomes.  Do not use unnecessarily large
        subnet masks.  If you setup your LAN as 10.0.0.0/8, but only have
        100 hosts on it, you're unnecessarily limiting your ability to
        add VPN networks anywhere in the 10.x.x.x space.  
        </para>

    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
        <para>If m0n0wall is not the default gateway on the LAN where it is installed,
        you must add static routes to whatever system is the default gateway, pointing the
        remote VPN subnet to the LAN IP of m0n0wall.
        </para>    
    </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You will need to either control or be in contact with the person
        who does control the other VPN concentrator. If it is another m0n0wall
        system, then share this document with the other administrator.  If it
        isn't then have them consult the documentation that came with the IPsec 
        device they are using.</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Host and application level security become more important when
        connecting multiple networks, how much depending on how much you trust
        the other network.  The VPN tunnel <emphasis>will not respond to firewall
        rules</emphasis> at the time of this writing, so you will not be able to
        limit which hosts can be accessed by users across the VPN connection.  If
        a worm would get into the network you are connected to via VPN, it could
        easily spread to your network.  If a system on the remote network is
        compromized by an attacker, he could easily hop over the VPN to attack
        your systems without any firewall protection.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Pay attention to what you are doing!  If you have a VPN to your
        office, and a VPN to your friend's home network, your friend can now
        hop over to your company's network from your network.  Or, if your
        friend gets infected with a worm, it could then infect your machines
        and continue to propagate over the VPN connection to your office.
        Most companies would probably fire you if your friend was caught on
        their network.  Best bet here is if you have a site to site VPN into
        your network at work, do not connect with friends, or use one network
        and firewall for accessing work and one for accessing your friend's
        network.</para>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

    <para>Ok now that we have the basics let's get started on the firewall
    settings.</para>

  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ipsec-tunnels.html"?>

    <title>Configuring the VPN Tunnel</title>

    <para>Log into your m0n0wall and click <emphasis role="bold">IPsec
    </emphasis>, under <emphasis role="bold">VPN</emphasis>.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="3.5902in" fileref="screens/ipsec/vpn-ipsec.png"
                     width="5.9945in" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>Ok now we need to add a VPN connection, to do this click on the
    <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="0.1772in" fileref="screens/ipsec/buttonplus.png"
                     width="0.1772in" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> icon.</para>

    <para>You will be presented with a great form, I will be pasting screen
    shots of each section as we discuss it.</para>

    <para>The first area is the one you use to establish what network ranges
    will use this IPSEC tunnel.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="3.6193in"
                     fileref="screens/ipsec/vpn-ipsec-edit.png"
                     width="5.9965in" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>This is the first set of fields that we need to concentrate on.
    Later, when testing your tunnel, you can actually fail to establish level
    2 connection if this data is incorrect. I will note what to pay particular
    attention to as we go along.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Mode, this is a hard set option and frankly you don’t need to
        change it (nor can you.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Disabled, this is a great “on / off” button if you need to
        disable the tunnel for what ever reason. Simply select the edit or
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata depth="0.1772in"
                         fileref="screens/ipsec/buttonedit.png"
                         width="0.1772in" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> from the main VPN: IPsec window and click this
        checkbox element, then select apply at the bottom of the page. When
        you need the tunnel again, reverse the process.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Interface, this is how you determine which part of your network
        will be the termination point (end point) for the VPN Tunnel. If you
        are connecting to a remote server, then WAN is your option.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Local subnet. This is where you can set which parts, hosts, or
        the entire LAN can be accessed from the other side of the VPN tunnel.
        The easiest thing to do is to set the LAN subnet as the option; this
        means your entire LAN will be accessible from the remote network.
        IMPORTANT: The other end of the tunnel has this same field, well it
        probably has 99% of these fields actually, make sure the other end is
        set exactly as you set this end. E.g. if you said “Single host” in
        this section and entered the IP address of that host, the other person
        would set that host in his “Remote Subnet” field. The same goes for
        you, and with that mentioned we move to the next field.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Remote Subnet. This is more than just labeling which hosts and /
        or host you want to access on the other network, as mentioned in item
        4 it is paramount that you set this exactly like the other end’s
        “local subnet” section. If not, level 2 of the VPN connection will
        fail and traffic will not pass from one VPN segment to the
        other.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Description: It is a good practice to always leave notes about
        why you are doing something. I suggest you enter something about what
        this VPN tunnel is used for, or about the remote end of the tunnel to
        remind yourself who/what it is.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Ok all the basic for the routing have been established. Now we move
    on to phase 1 of the VPN authentication process.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="3.3783in" fileref="screens/ipsec/phase1.png"
                     width="5.9929in" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>Okay the easy part of the VPN tunnel. The trick here, and even in
    phase 2, is to make sure that both VPN servers have EXACTLY THE SAME
    SETTINGS for all of these fields. Well okay, they will have different “My
    identifier” but make darn sure that they know each others names… more on
    that later.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Negotiation mode: This is the type of authentication security
        that will be used. Unless you are under close watch by someone with
        paranormal like craziness, just leave this as aggressive. It is indeed
        far faster and will insure that your VPN tunnel will rebuild itself
        quickly and probably won’t time out an application if the tunnel was
        down when the resource on the other end was requested. (more about
        that under Lifetime)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>My identifier: This is the key to probably 90% of the email on
        the list where people seem to not get the VPN tunnel up, or want to
        know how to do this with dynamic IP addresses, etc. Very simple, set
        your identifier to something that isn’t going to change. So if you
        leave it as My IP address (* This will be the IP address of the
        “interface” you listed in the first section. *) then make sure that IP
        is static and persistent. If you use a DHCP assigned address then I
        would suggest using domain name instead This is because domain name
        can be completely your own even if you do not own the domain name.
        Make yours sexylovemonkey.com just for fun. ;)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Encryption Algorithm: 3DES is the world de facto… if you are
        connecting to another m0n0wall, or a system that will support it,
        change this to Blowfish. It is a more secure and about twice as fast!
        Now of course, if you are trying to connect to a VPN device that only
        supports DES then you will need to downgrade and hope no one decrypts
        your key exchange. MAKE SURE BOTH VPN DEVICES ARE USING THE SAME
        ENCRYPTION ALGORITHM.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hash Algorithm: this is the hash used for checksum. MD5 is a
        good choice, SHA1 is the new up and comer and it is more reliable then
        MD5, but not all things support it. Again make sure you are using the
        same setting as the other end of the tunnel, and if you can use SHA1
        go for it!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DH Key Group: Most systems will support at least up to 1024 bit.
        This is a good place to stick to, going with more will eat up more
        resources and less makes your tunnel less-secure.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Lifetime: This field is far more important then it appears. This
        lifetime, as opposed to the one in phase 2, is how long your end will
        wait for phase 1 to be completed. I suggest using 28800 in this
        field.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Pre-Shared Key: Contrary to some suggestions this key must be
        exactly the same on both VPN routers. It is case sensitive, and it
        does support special characters. I suggest using both. E.x.
        f00m0nk3y@BubbaLand</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Okay if you managed to coordinate and get both VPN systems set the
    same all should be good for phase 1. We really don’t want to stop here, so
    let’s go right into phase 2.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="4.3366in" fileref="screens/ipsec/phase2.png"
                     width="5.9917in" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>Phase 2 is what builds the actual tunnel, sets the protocol to use,
    and sets the length of time to keep the tunnel up when there is no traffic
    on it.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Protocol: ESP is the de facto on what most VPN systems use as a
        transport protocol. I suggest leaving this as is. Note: The system
        should auto generate a firewall rule for you to allow ESP or AH to the
        endpoint of the VPN. We will check this later, if it does not you will
        need to make a firewall rule allowing ESP (or AH if you changed this)
        traffic to the interface you established as your end point of the
        tunnel. I will outline that after figure 5.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Encryption algorithms: Ok here is the deal on this. Like before
        in phase 1, make sure you are setting the algorithm exactly as it is
        set on the other VPN server. You can use several; when you do so
        everything you select is available for use. Honestly I like to keep
        things simple so I recommend only checking the one you are going to
        use. With m0n0wall to m0n0wall use Blowfish for speed and security
        over 3DES.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hash algorithms: again just as in phase 1 you want to make sure
        your selected hash matches the one on the other end. And like in step
        2, don’t add things you don’t need. SHA1 is the suggestion if you can,
        but MD5 is always a good alternative.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PFS key group: this works exactly like it does in phase 1. I
        suggest using 1024 bit, the default is off.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Lifetime: This is the lifetime the negotiated keys will be valid
        for. Do not set this to too high of a number. E.g. more than about a
        day (86400) as doing so will give people more time to crack your key.
        Don’t be over paranoid either; there is no need to set this to 20
        minutes or something like that. Honestly, one day is probably
        good.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click Save</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click Apply Changes</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ipsec-behindfirewall.html"?>

    <title>What if your m0n0wall isn’t the main Internet Firewall?</title>

    <para>FIXME - In some cases you have a firewall or router with layer 2 routing
    (protocol ACLs) sitting in front of your m0n0wall. If this is the case you
    will need to port forward ESP or AH (depending on which one you chose) to
    the m0n0wall. (NOTE: if you are running NAT on that firewall AH will not
    be an option.)</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Example: m0n0wall behind a router</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="screens/ipsec/routing.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>
</chapter>