<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: setup.xml,v 1.3 2005/10/08 22:56:11 chris Exp $ -->
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="setup.html"?>

  <title>Setup</title>

  <para>This chapter acts as a quick reference for those who are familiar 
  with installing and configuring m0n0wall.  If you need more than a quick
  reference on what commands to use to write a CD, CF, HD, etc. please see 
  the Quick Start Guide appropriate to your platform.</para>

  <para><ulink url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/quickstartsoekris/">Soekris Quick 
  Start Guide</ulink></para>

  <para><ulink url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/quickstartpc/">PC Quick Start 
  Guide</ulink></para>

  <para><ulink url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/quickstartwrap/">WRAP Quick Start
  Guide</ulink></para>

  <sect1 id="Setup.Getting">
    <?dbhtml filename="setup-getting.html"?>

    <title id="Setup.Getting.title">Getting the Software</title>

    <para>There are ready-made binary images for the net45xx/net48xx
    communication computers from <ulink url="http://www.soekris.com">Soekris Engineering</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://www.pcengines.ch/wrap.htm">
     Wireless Router Application Platform</ulink> (WRAP) from <ulink url="http://www.pcengines.ch/">PC Engines</ulink>, a CF/IDE HD image for most standard
    PCs (embedded ones may work, too), a CD-ROM (ISO) image for standard PCs
    as well as a tarball of the root filesystem.</para>


    <para>To download the software for your platform, point your web browser
    at <ulink
    url="http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/downloads.php">http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/downloads.php</ulink>
    and select the appropriate download link from that page. Download the file
    to your working machine from which you will be writing to either a CD-R or
    a CompactFlash as described in the <link linkend="Setup.Installing">next
    section</link>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Setup.Installing">
    <?dbhtml filename="setup-installing.html"?>

    <title id="Setup.Installing.title">Installing the Software</title>

    <para>m0n0wall is designed to boot and run from either a CD image or a
    CompactFlash (CF) card or IDE hard disk. After downloading the appropriate
    image file, prepare the CD or CF.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Preparing a bootable CD</title>

      <para>You can run m0n0wall on a standard PC with a CD-ROM drive and a
      floppy drive. A hard disk is not required. m0n0wall will boot from the
      CD and run from memory. The floppy is used only to store your m0n0wall
      configuration. If you want to run m0n0wall on a standard PC with a hard
      disk rather than a CD, follow the directions in the <link
      linkend="Setup.Installing.CF">next section</link>.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Download the ISO image as described in <link
          endterm="Setup.Getting.title"
          linkend="Setup.Getting"></link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Burn the ISO image onto a CD-R (or -RW):</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>FreeBSD (ATAPI recorder):</para>
              <programlisting>burncd -s max -e data cdrom-xxx.iso fixate</programlisting>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Linux (ATAPI w/ SCSI emulation):</para>
                <para>First, determine your burning device's SCSI ID/LUN with the
                following command:</para>
                <programlisting>linuxbox# cdrecord --scanbus
Cdrecord-Clone 2.01 (i686-pc-linux-gnu) Copyright (C) 1995-2004 Jörg Schilling
Linux sg driver version: 3.1.25
Using libscg version 'schily-0.8'.
scsibus0:
    0,0,0   100) 'LITE-ON ' 'COMBO LTC-48161H' 'KH0F' Removable CD-ROM
                 </programlisting>   
    
                <para>Note the SCSI ID/LUN is 0,0,0. Burn the image as in the following
                example (replacing &lt;max speed&gt; with the speed of your burner):</para>
                <programlisting>cdrecord --dev=0,0,0 --speed=&lt;max speed&gt; cdrom-xxx.iso</programlisting>
            </listitem>
    
            <listitem>
              <para>Windows: use your favorite burning program (e.g. Nero) to
              record the ISO image (2048 bytes/sector, Mode-1)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Format a standard 1.44 MB diskette <emphasis role="bold">with
          MS-DOS/FAT file system</emphasis>.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>FreeBSD:</para>

              <programlisting>fdformat -f 1440 /dev/fd0 &amp;&amp; newfs_msdos -L "m0n0wallcfg" -f 1440 /dev/fd0</programlisting>

              <para>Note: you can omit the fdformat step if the floppy disk is
              already (low-level) formatted.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Windows:</para>

              <programlisting>format A:</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Make sure your m0n0wall PC is set to boot from CD-ROM and
      <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> from floppy.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Setup.Installing.CF">
      <title id="Setup.Installing.CF.title">Preparing a CompactFlash or IDE
      Hard Disk</title>

      <para>You can run m0n0wall on a system which uses a CompactFlash (CF)
      card as its primary disk, such as the <ulink
      url="http://www.soekris.com">Soekris</ulink> boxes, or on a standard PC
      with an IDE hard disk. m0n0wall will load from the CF card or disk and
      then run from memory. It does not swap to the CF card or disk, nor does
      it write anything to it except when you change and save your
      configuration.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Download the appropriate raw CF/IDE image as described in
          <link endterm="Setup.Getting.title"
          linkend="Setup.Getting"></link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Write the image to a sufficiently large CF card or disk (at
          least 5 MB). Extra space on the CF card or disk is ignored; there is
          no benefit to using one larger than the image size.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>FreeBSD:</para>

              <programlisting>gzcat net45xx-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/rad[n] bs=16k</programlisting>

              <para>where n = the ad device number of your CF card or IDE disk
              (check dmesg); use net48xx-xxx.img for net4801, wrap-xxx.img for
              WRAP, and generic-pc-xxx.img for an IDE disk on a PC instead of
              net45xx-xxx.img.</para>

              <para><emphasis>Ignore the warning about trailing garbage - it's
              because of the digital signature.</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Linux:</para>

              <programlisting>gunzip -c net45xx-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/hdX bs=16k</programlisting>

              <para>where X = the IDE device name of your CF card or IDE disk
              (check with hdparm -i /dev/hdX) - some adapters, particularly
              USB, may show up under SCSI emulation as /dev/sdX.</para>

              <para><emphasis>Ignore the warning about trailing garbage - it's
              because of the digital signature.</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Windows:</para>

              <programlisting>physdiskwrite [-u] net45xx-xxx.img</programlisting>

              <para>where physdiskwrite is v0.3 or later of the physdiskwrite
              program available from the m0n0wall web site <ulink
              url="http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/physdiskwrite.php">physdiskwrite
              page</ulink>. Use the -u flag (without the square brackets) if
              the target disk is &gt; 800 MB - make very sure you've selected
              the right disk!!</para>
              
              <para>To ensure you have selected the appropriate disk, run physdiskwrite prior to inserting the media
              you're planning to write, and make note of its output.</para>
              
              <programlisting>physdiskwrite v0.5 by Manuel Kasper &lt;mk@neon1.net&gt;

Searching for physical drives...

Information for \\.\PhysicalDrive0:
      Windows:       cyl: 14593
                     tpc: 255
                     spt: 63
      C/H/S:         16383/16/63
      Model:         ST3120026A
      Serial number: 3JT1V2FS
      Firmware rev.: 3.06</programlisting>
              
            <para>You now know the drives currently in the system, so you know which
            you don't want to use.  Make note of the model and serial number.
            Add the drive or CompactFlash card you wish
            to write to, and run physdiskwrite again.  You'll now see an additional
            drive in the output, and by referring back to when you ran the command
            earlier, you will know by process of elimination which drive is the one
            you want to write.  </para>
              
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Alternative means of installation</title>
        
        <para>For alternative means of installing m0n0wall, see the <link linkend="OtherDoc.Installation">
            Installation section</link> of the Other Documentation chapter.
        </para>
            
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="setup-booting.html"?>

    <title>Booting m0n0wall</title>

    <para>The first time you boot your system to run m0n0wall, you must
    configure it. Once configured, it will automatically run m0n0wall with
    your configuration when booted.</para>

    <para>When booting your m0n0wall system for the first time:</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Insert the m0n0wall CD, CF or disk you prepared according to the
        instructions <link linkend="Setup.Installing">above</link>. On a CD
        system, also insert the formatted and blank floppy disk. Make sure the
        floppy is writable (not write-protected) and formatted with the FAT file
        system.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ensure that the system boots from the CD, CF or disk. You may
        need to enter the BIOS on your system to configure this.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ensure that the system console is available. On a PC, make sure
        keyboard and monitor are connected to the system. On a Soekris box,
        the serial port is the console; connect it to a terminal, or use a
        null-modem cable to connect it to a serial port on another computer
        running a terminal emulator.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>On a Soekris box or WRAP board, make sure the console speed is
        set to 9600 bps in the BIOS (set ConSpeed=9600 for Soekris
        boxes).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Connect the system to the network.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Boot the system and wait for the console menu to appear. Assign
        the network interface ports as described in the <link
        linkend="Config.Console">following chapter</link>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Complete the configuration of your m0n0wall system by using the
        webGUI as described <link linkend="Config.WebGUI">below</link>. Save
        your configuration file to your working computer as a backup.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>It seems that some Soekris net45xx's have a bug where sometimes a
      character is sent twice over the serial console, but another character
      is dropped instead. This is solved with a BIOS upgrade from Soekris
      (version 1.15a or later).</para>
    </note>

    <para>After you have finished editing your configuration, you are ready to
    go. You do not need to reboot your m0n0wall box, although you may wish to
    do so to see that it boots directly into operation.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
