<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: configure.xml,v 1.3 2005/09/26 00:05:23 chris Exp $ -->
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="initial-configuration.html"?>

  <title>Initial Configuration</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Initial Configuration</title>

    <para>By default, m0n0wall enables its DHCP server on its LAN interface,
    and configures the LAN interface with IP address 192.168.1.1. If you have
    an existing DHCP server, and/or wish to use a different IP subnet on your
    LAN, you will need to first connect via the PC's keyboard/ monitor or
    serial console interface.</para>

    <note>
       Unless you know what you're doing, we 

      <emphasis>strongly recommend</emphasis>

       not changing the LAN IP address or pre-configured DHCP settings to avoid difficulties caused by misconfiguration. 
    </note>

    <para>If you do not need to change the interface assignments, LAN IP
    address, or DHCP server settings, you can skip ahead to the <link
    linkend="Client.Machine.Config"> next chapter</link>. Otherwise, below are
    steps to make changes to the default configuration using either your
    m0n0wall PC's keyboard/ monitor or serial console interface.</para>

    <para>In general, connecting to a m0n0wall PC with a keyboard/ monitor
    will prove easier for the first time users than connecting to the serial
    console interface. This is because there are many different console
    configurations possible for any given PC, sometimes with jumpers,
    sometimes in the system BIOS.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The default configuration for m0n0wall does not activate a
      wireless interface, even if one is installed. That means that you can
      not change the default configuration using only a wireless connection.
      You must be connected by Ethernet or Serial console cable to make the
      first configuration change.</para>
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Connecting to the keyboard/ monitor</title>

    <para>If the m0n0wall PC already has a keyboard and monitor it will be
    easy to verify that the boot up has gone well and to make any necessary
    changes to the default configuration. During the start up of the m0n0wall
    computer the status will be output to the screen. When the boot process is
    finished a cursor prompt will be blinking and awaiting your
    command.</para>

    <para>Assuming all has gone as explained above, you can now proceed to
    <xref linkend="Config.ConsoleSetup" xrefstyle="page" />.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Connecting.Serial.Console">
    <?dbhtml filename="initial-serialconsole.html"?>

    <title>Connecting to the serial console</title>

    <para>Accessing a PC computer by its serial interface is useful for
    m0n0wall PC's without a keyboard or mouse connected to them or for
    troubleshooting. The simplest configuration however is to simply connect a
    client PC temporarily to the m0n0wall PC as a DHCP client and make your
    initial configuration using the web interface.</para>

    <para>However, instructions are below for those that still wish to connect
    using a serial console interface.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Getting the appropriate cable</title>

      <para>First you need a null modem cable, <emphasis>not</emphasis> a
      straight through serial cable. For the appropriate pin-out, see <ulink
      url="http://www.nullmodem.com/NullModem.htm">this page</ulink>. You can
      purchase a null modem cable at most any store that carries computer
      cables, or from a variety of online sources. (<ulink
      url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=null+modem+cable">Froogle
      link</ulink> for null modem cables)</para>

      <para>Connect the null modem cable to your embedded device and
      PC.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Connecting to the serial console</title>

      <para>For Windows users, HyperTerminal isn't great, but it gets the job
      done. You can find it under Start, Programs, Communications,
      HyperTerminal. If you cannot find it on your system, you can download it
      for free <ulink
      url="http://www.hilgraeve.com/htpe/">here</ulink>.</para>

      <para>After opening HyperTerminal, you will see the New Connection
      screen.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/hyperterminal/newconnection.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Type in something for the connection name and click OK.</para>

      <para>Next, you'll see the "Connect to" screen. Select the COM port
      number of the serial port in your PC. If you do not know which it is,
      trial and error might be the easiest way to determine this. Start with
      COM1, and try other ports if necessary. In this case, I know my serial
      port is COM1.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/hyperterminal/connectto.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Now you'll see the Connection Properties screen. If you have
      changed the console speed on your PC, you will need to change the "Bits
      per second" field accordingly.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/hyperterminal/connectionproperties.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Click OK after filling in the Connection Properties appropriately,
      and you will have a blank HyperTerminal screen. Now power on your
      device.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Config.ConsoleSetup">
    <?dbhtml filename="initial-m0n0wall-console.html"?>

    <title>m0n0wall Console Setup</title>

    <para>To recap from earlier, your system is now ready to be configured.
    You are able to view the keyboard/video output or a serial console at
    38400 bps (or via a video card and monitor) and have the media you loaded
    with m0n0wall earlier installed in the target machine.</para>

    <para>When your system finishes booting, you will see the m0n0wall
    console.</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced">
*** This is m0n0wall, version 1.2
    built on Sun Aug 22 11:41:15 CEST 2004 for WRAP
    Copyright (C) 2002-2005 by Manuel Kasper. All rights reserved.
    Visit http://m0n0.ch/wall for updates.
    
    
    LAN IP address: 192.168.1.1
    
    Port configuration:
    
    LAN  -&gt; sis0
    WAN  -&gt; sis1


m0n0wall console setup
**********************
1) Interfaces: assign network ports
2) Set up LAN IP address
3) Reset webGUI password
4) Reset to factory defaults
5) Reboot system
        </literallayout>

    <para>Although this example shows sis0 and sis1 as the two Ethernet
    interfaces these names depend on the Ethernet cards that are installed.
    These 4 characters simply identify the driver used to access the Ethernet
    card and the number of cards that are using the same driver. Other
    possible Ethernet interface names include: bge, em, gx, nge, ti, txp, dc,
    fxp, sis, ste, tl, tx, xl.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Console Setup Menu Options</title>

      <para>First I will explain the purpose of each menu option.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 1</emphasis> allows you to assign
      network interfaces to be used for LAN, WAN, and OPT networks, as well as
      allowing you to configure VLAN's.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 2</emphasis> allows you to set the
      LAN IP address to something other than the default 192.168.1.1.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 3</emphasis> allows you to reset the
      webGUI password if you have forgotten it.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 4</emphasis> lets you reset the
      system to factory default configuration. If you get stuck at some point
      during configuration, sometimes it is easier to start over from
      scratch.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 5</emphasis> lets you reboot the
      system.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="initial-assigning-interfaces.html"?>

    <title>Assigning Interfaces</title>

    <para>Press 1 at the console setup screen if you wish to reassign your
    network interfaces.</para>

    <note>
       To avoid potential problems with mis-assignment, we recommend leaving your interface assignments as is. 
    </note>

    <para>Below are the steps to change the assignment of which Ethernet card
    is used for which network connection. For example if you had both a 10Mbps
    and 100Mbps Ethernet card you would typically want the higher speed card
    (or cards) on the LAN and the slower cards on the WAN (assuming that your
    WAN Internet connection is less than 10Mbps).</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced">
Enter a number: 1

Valid interfaces are:

sis0    00:0c:29:96:5e:de
sis1    00:0c:29:96:53:e8

Do you want to set up VLANs first?
If you're not going to use VLANs, or only for optional interfaes, you
should say no here and use the webGUI to configure VLANs later, if required.

Do you want to set up VLANs now? (y/n) 
    </literallayout>

    <para>As this guide only leads you through a simple two interface
    configuration, we will press n and hit enter here to skip VLAN
    configuration. If you need VLAN support, configure it in the webGUI after
    this initial configuration is complete. You can use the Valid interfaces
    list to see how your installed Ethernet cards are identified by the
    m0n0wall operating system.</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced">
If you don't know the names of your interfaces, you may choose to use
auto-detection.  In that case, disconnect all interfaces before you begin,
and reconnect each one when prompted to do so.

Enter the LAN interface name or 'a' for auto-detection:
    </literallayout>

    <para>Enter the name of the desired LAN interface by selecting one of the
    Ethernet card names such as "sis0" and press Enter.</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced">
Enter the WAN interface name or 'a' for auto-detection
(or nothing if finished):
</literallayout>

    <para>Enter one of the remaining available interfaces and press
    Enter.</para>

    <para>Next you will be prompted for assigning optional interfaces. You can
    do this later through the webGUI if need be. Without entering anything,
    hit ENTER at this prompt.</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced">
Enter the Optional 1 interface name or 'a' for auto-detection
(or nothing if finished):
</literallayout>

    <para>You will now see how your interfaces have been configured.</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced">
The interfaces will be assigned as follows:

LAN  -&gt; sis1
WAN  -&gt; sis0

The firewall will reboot after saving the changes.

Do you want to proceed? (y/n)
    </literallayout>

    <para>This confirms how the interfaces will be assigned. Press y and hit
    enter here to restart the firewall for the changes to take effect. To
    discard your changes, enter n and press Enter. If all of your hardware and
    cables are correctly installed you should be able to reach the m0n0wall at
    the 192.168.1.1 IP address from a client computer.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Changing the LAN IP and/or DHCP server settings.</title>

    <para>View this online tutorial for a how to on <ulink
    url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/tutorials/console/lanip/changeLANIP.htm">changing
    your LAN IP address and/or DHCP server settings</ulink>.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>If you already have a DHCP server on your LAN network DO NOT
      connect the m0n0wall to your LAN network until you have first disabled
      the DHCP server on the m0n0wall. Otherwise your m0n0wall might respond
      to a DHCP client computer on your LAN before your normal server and
      thereby give incorrect information to the IP requesting computer.</para>
    </warning>
  </sect1>
</chapter>