<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="hardware.html"?>
  <title>Selecting Your Hardware</title> 

 <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-selection.html"?>
    
    <title>Choosing Your Hardware</title>
    
    <para>The hardware you choose will depend on what features you will use, how
    much bandwidth you have, and some matters of personal preference (embedded
    device vs. standard PC).  </para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Hardware Reliability</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>While m0n0wall will run on very old hardware, keep in mind the reliability
    of older hardware is certainly questionable.  If uptime isn't critically
    important, don't hesitate to use old hardware.  If this is in a production
    business environment, a Soekris or WRAP board could save you some explaining
    down the road on why your internet connection went down.</para>
    
    <para>If you are using old hardware, make sure you have a contingency plan
    should it fail.  Keeping a spare machine with your current m0n0wall configuration
    loaded, ready to be used if necessary, would be a good idea.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Processor</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>For most broadband connections, any 486 or faster will be sufficient.
    If you have less than 10 Mb of internet bandwidth (combined upload and
    download speed), an embedded device like the WRAP or Soekris platforms, or
    an old 486 will suffice.  For 10 Mb up to a full T3 or more, a Pentium II or III PC
    system, or embedded device like a NexCom is more appropriate.  See Chapter
    2 of the Users Guide for further details on compatible hardware.</para>
    
    <para>For connections faster than a T3 using many VPN sessions, you will
    likely want to use a customized version of m0n0wall specifically built for
    your requirements, and high end Pentium 4, Xeon, or similar hardware.  This
    is beyond the scope of this document.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">RAM</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>We recommend 64 MB of RAM minimum.  32 MB RAM has been reported to
    work fine on a CD/floppy setup with no VPN configurations.  It has been
    reported to run out of RAM with a few active VPN tunnels.  Hard drive or
    CF installs are not recommended with less than 64 MB RAM because you will
    probably run out of RAM during upgrades and m0n0wall has no swap, so the
    upgrade will fail.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Hardware Sizing</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>Keep in mind there is no standard "if you have X internet connection
    and Y number of machines on your network, then you need Z hardware".  It
    varies depending on what services you will use, and your internet traffic
    characteristics.  The one thing that will require significantly more CPU,
    and/or a VPN accelerator card, is if you'll require more than a couple
    Mbps of VPN traffic for extended periods.
    </para>
    
    <para>To get an idea of network throughput for Soekris and WRAP boards, see
    <ulink url="http://m0n0.ch/wall/docbook/faq-performancespecifications.html">
    this FAQ entry.</ulink></para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Cards</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>You will need at least two network cards in the hardware you are
    using.  Most any are compatible, check the <ulink url="http://m0n0.ch/wall/docbook/hardware-ethernet.html">
    Users Guide</ulink> for further details.
    ISA cards are much more problematic than PCI cards, and PCI cards are
    readily available and cheap if you need to buy some.  </para>
    
    <para>For this document, we will assume these are two Ethernet interfaces.
    You can have additional interfaces installed in the system, but do not
    configure them during this process.  Documentation in the Users Guide will
    soon be available to assist you in setting up additional LAN interfaces,
    DMZ interfaces, wireless setups, etc.</para>

    <sect2>
        <title>Storage Medium</title>
    
        <para>m0n0wall will run off of a hard drive, CD-ROM and floppy, or
            CompactFlash card.  The pros and cons of each follow.  Choose the
            one most appropriate for your situation, taking available hardware
            and other factors into account.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hard Drive</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>Hard drives are readily available, and if you are using a standard
        PC, you'll likely have one in it.  The hard drive installation is
        remotely upgradeable via the webGUI, so it's a better choice over a CD/floppy setup in
        many instances.  The likelihood of a hard drive failure is pretty high,
        given that the hardware being used is likely old.  An IDE to
        CompactFlash adapter should be considered where hardware failure cannot
        be tolerated, since the likelihood of failure is much less with a
        CompactFlash card.  Such an adapter can be purchased new for about $10
        USD.  <ulink url="
        http://www.pcengines.ch/cflash.htm">PC Engines</ulink> sells them,
        amongst other vendors.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">CD/floppy Setup</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>The CD/floppy setup works by booting m0n0wall off of the CD and
        storing the configuration on a FAT formatted floppy. This is a good
        solution on systems that you are physically close to very frequently
        (remote upgrades via webGUI not possible).  Floppy disks are notorious
        for becoming corrupted, so it's even more important to make sure you
        keep a backup of your configuration.  Floppy disks have much more
        problems in environments that are dusty or dirty, so in those situations
        we would highly recommend choosing a different setup.</para>
        
        <para>The machine you are using must support CD booting (some 486 and
        Pentium systems do not).  You also must set the CD-ROM as the first
        boot device in the boot order in the system's BIOS so it doesn't attempt
        to boot off of the config floppy.  Consult your system or motherboard
        manual for information on how to configure that.
        </para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">CompactFlash</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>CompactFlash (CF) is a good choice for most any deployment.  CF
        cards are more reliable than hard drives and the floppy drives that
        hold the configuration in the CD/floppy setup, and are remotely
        upgradeable via the webGUI.  The downside is you might spend
        more money getting a CF setup working.  If you are not using an embedded
        device with an onboard CF adapter, you will have to spend about $10 USD
        on a IDE to CF adapter.  You'll need to purchase a CF card at least 8 MB
        in size.  I purchase used 8 MB CF cards off eBay to use for m0n0wall
        installations, and get them for $5-$10 USD each.  You may also need a CF
        reader on your PC to write the m0n0wall image to the CF card.  Those are
        approximately $30 USD.  So you could be looking at a total expenditure
        of about $50 USD.  But most any business environment should be able to
        justify such a small expenditure for the increase in reliability.</para>
      </sect2>

  </sect1>
  
</chapter>