<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Getting and Installing m0n0wall</title>

  <?dbhtml filename="setup.html"?>

  <para>The instructions below assume that you have a working PC computer with
  the proper cables and BIOS options chosen to boot from your selected media.
  It might save you some troubleshooting time if you first verify that your
  system is in working condition. One easy way to do this is to download or
  grab from a computer magazine a bootable Linux or BSD. These are often
  called Live-CD distributions and can autodetect most hardware and boot your
  system.</para>

  <sect1 id="Setup.ChoosingMedia">
    <?dbhtml filename="setup-choosingmedia.html"?>

    <title>Choosing your Media</title>

    <para>m0n0wall provides two options for PC users, either a CD and floppy
    setup or a hard disk setup. In either case you will need an existing
    computer to write to the Compact Flash or CDROM. In both cases you will
    download a m0n0wall file called an image that contains the bootable
    operating system. This image will be written to a media that your chosen
    m0n0wall computer can boot from.</para>

    <para>Your customized changes to the default configuration will be stored
    in active memory of the m0n0wall computer. In a CD/ floppy setup, the
    floppy will store this customized configuration. In a Hard Drive or CF
    Card setup, the media itself is also writable and can store the
    configuration. In all cases the configuration file can be downloaded from
    the web interface for external storage.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>It is recommended to always store an external backup of your
      configuration file in case of emergencies.</para>
    </tip>

    <sect2>
      <title>CD/Floppy Setup</title>

      <para>m0n0wall can run from a CD, with a floppy disk to save the
      configuration. This is typically a good way to try m0n0wall without
      actually overwriting a hard drive. However, we do not recommend it for
      production use, due to the likelihood of floppy disk or drive failure. A
      hard drive is far more reliable, and Compact Flash is even more reliable
      still.</para>

      <para>Starting in version 1.3 a flash drive can be used in place of a
      floppy disk for storing the configuration file.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Hard Drive or CF Card Setup</title>

      <para>Many users find that a Compact Flash card offers higher
      reliability than an old hard drive. A Compact Flash card can be used to
      boot a traditional PC when using a Compact Flash to IDE Adapter.</para>

      <para>You can also install m0n0wall to any hard drive of sufficient size
      (&gt;=8 MB in version 1.2 and &gt;10MB in version 1.3 and later), so
      basically any IDE hard drive ever made).</para>

      <para>The instructions for writing the m0n0wall image are the same as
      writing to a hard disk unless otherwise noted.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Setup.Installing">
    <?dbhtml filename="setup-installing.html"?>

    <title id="Setup.Installing.title">Getting and Installing the
    Software</title>

    <para>To download the generic-pc image or CD ISO, point your web browser
    to <ulink
    url="http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/downloads.php">http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/downloads.php</ulink>
    and select the generic-pc download link from that page. Download the file
    to the computer you plan to use for writing to the CompactFlash card or
    hard disk.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Installing the Standard PC by Hard Disk</title>

      <para>Installation on a standard PC requires the following steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>download the raw CF/IDE image (generic-pc)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>write the image to a CF card (&gt; 5 MB) or an IDE hard disk,
          either with dd under FreeBSD or under Windows with physdiskwrite. A
          more detailed description of writing the image to these media is in
          the following section</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>put the CF card/HD into the target PC</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>plug the PC into the network (LAN/WAN/...).</para>

          <caution>
            <para>If you have an existing DHCP server, and/or wish to use a
            different IP subnet on your LAN, you will need to first connect
            via the PC's keyboard/ monitor or serial console interface as
            described in the Initial Configuration chapter.</para>
          </caution>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>power up the PC</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Now that your system has booted using the m0n0wall software
      continue to the section <xref linkend="setup-finalprep" />.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Writing the Image File</title>

      <para>If you are installing to a standard PC using an IDE or CF disk,
      you need to write the image to a sufficiently large CF card or hard disk
      (at least 10 MB for the generic-PC image in version 1.3). Extra space on
      the CF card or drive is ignored; there is no benefit to using one larger
      than 8 MB other than possibly compatibility on future releases.</para>

      <para>The following sections will cover how to write the CF card in
      Windows, FreeBSD, and Linux. A summary is below with details following
      for each operating system.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Windows:</para>

          <para>(use the -u flag if the target disk is &gt; 800 MB - make very
          sure you've selected the right disk!!) <programlisting>physdiskwrite [-u] generic-pc-xxx.img</programlisting>(you
          must use v0.3 or later!)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>FreeBSD:</para>

          <para><programlisting>gzcat generic-pc-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/rad[n] bs=16k</programlisting>where
          n = the ad device number of your CF card (check dmesg) (ignore the
          warning about trailing garbage - it's because of the digital
          signature)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Linux:</para>

          <para><programlisting>gunzip -c generic-pc-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/hdX bs=16k</programlisting>where
          X = the IDE device name of your HD/CF card (check with hdparm -i
          /dev/hdX) - some CF adapters, particularly USB, may show up under
          SCSI emulation as /dev/sdX (ignore the warning about trailing
          garbage - it's because of the digital signature)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect3>
        <title>Windows</title>

        <para>For Windows you will be downloading physdiskwrite from the
        m0n0wall web site. This is a small Windows NT/2000/XP command line
        tool that makes it possible to write disk images onto raw disks, like
        CF cards. It currently has a few rough edges, most notably in the
        selection of the device to be written – you have to decide which
        device is the right one by looking at the C/H/S values (though if the
        CF card was the last device to be connected to the system, it usually
        shows up as the last one in the list).</para>

        <para>Note that the C/H/S values may be incorrect for CF cards – looks
        like this is a bug in Windows. There is some protection against
        accidentally overwriting your hard disk, but then again,<emphasis
        role="bold"> I CAN'T TAKE ANY RESPONSIBILITY FOR LOST DATA – YOU USE
        THIS PROGRAM ON YOUR OWN RISK.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Manuel Kasper's (author of m0n0wall) physdiskwrite should be
        used on Windows to write the CF card. Download it from the m0n0wall
        web site's <ulink url="http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/physdiskwrite.php">
        physdiskwrite page</ulink>.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Note to Windows Vista users: physdiskwrite works with Vista,
          but you must make sure to run it as administrator (simply having
          admin rights isn't enough), or it won't find any disks. One way to
          do this is to create a shortcut to cmd.exe, then right-click it and
          select "run as administrator". Then you can launch physdiskwrite
          from the command prompt window that appears, and it should work
          fine.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Save physdiskwrite.exe and the downloaded m0n0wall image in the
        same directory on your hard drive, then open a Windows Command Prompt
        (click Start, Run, type in cmd and click OK).</para>

        <para>Plug in your CF card reader/writer and insert your CF card. If
        you are connecting your hard drive you can either connect it directly
        to your computer or through a fire wire or USB adaptor for external
        drives.</para>

        <para>'cd' into the directory containing physdiskwrite and the
        m0n0wall image and run the following:</para>

        <programlisting>physdiskwrite generic-pc-xxx.img</programlisting>

        <para>Replacing generic-pc-xxx.img with the name of the generic-pc
        image you downloaded.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>Windows users can just simply drag-and-drop the image file
          onto the physdiskwrite.exe icon.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>You will see output similar to the following:</para>

        <programlisting>
physdiskwrite v0.5 by Manuel Kasper &lt;mk@neon1.net&gt;

Searching for physical drives...

Information for \\.\PhysicalDrive0:
   Windows:       cyl: 14593
                  tpc: 255
                  spt: 63
   C/H/S:         16383/16/63
   Model:         ST3120026A
   Serial number: 3JT1V2FS
   Firmware rev.: 3.06

Information for \\.\PhysicalDrive1:
   Windows:       cyl: 1
                  tpc: 255
                  spt: 63</programlisting>

        <para>You will see all the hard drives in your system listed, as well
        as the compact flash card. Since we did not run <emphasis>
        physdiskwrite -u</emphasis>, physdiskwrite will refuse to write to any
        drive over 2 GB. This is a protection so you don't accidentally
        overwrite your hard drive.</para>

        <warning>
          <para>If you are using physdiskwrite.exe to write to a second hard
          disk be very careful that you identify the correct disk before
          writing to it (i.e. do not write the image to your own computer's
          boot disk).</para>
        </warning>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>FreeBSD</title>

        <para>The procedures to image a CompactFlash card depend upon the type
        of adapter you are using. The CF card will either appear as a SCSI or
        IDE hard drive.</para>

        <para>Run the command <emphasis role="bold">atacontrol
        list</emphasis>. You will get output similar to the following:</para>

        <literallayout class="monospaced">
su-3.00# atacontrol list
ATA channel 0:
Master: ad0 &lt;WDC WD200EB-75CSF0/04.01B04&gt; ATA/ATAPI revision 5
Slave: ad1 &lt;WDC WD800AB-22CBA0/03.06A03&gt; ATA/ATAPI revision 5
ATA channel 1:
Master: acd0 &lt;_NEC CD-RW NR-7800A/10DA&gt; ATA/ATAPI revision 0
Slave: no device present
            </literallayout>

        <para>Then run the command <emphasis role="bold">camcontrol
        devlist</emphasis>. You will see output similar to the
        following:</para>

        <literallayout class="monospaced">
su-2.05b# camcontrol devlist
&lt;ADAPTEC RAID-5 320R&gt; at scbus2 target 0 lun 0 (pass0,da0)
&lt;SEAGATE ST39204LC 0005&gt; at scbus2 target 3 lun 0 (pass1,da1)
&lt;ESG-SHV SCA HSBP M10 0.05&gt; at scbus2 target 6 lun 0 (pass2)                
            </literallayout>

        <para>You will find your CF card somewhere in the above output. Make
        note of its device name (adX or daX).</para>

        <para>Run the following command, replacing adX with your CF device as
        determined above, and generic-pc-xxx.img with the name of the m0n0wall
        image you downloaded.</para>

        <computeroutput>gzcat generic-pc-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/adX
        bs=16k</computeroutput>

        <para>
          <emphasis>Ignore the warning about trailing garbage - it's because
          of the digital signature.</emphasis>
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Linux</title>

        <programlisting>gunzip -c generic-pc-xx-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/hdX bs=16k</programlisting>

        <para>where X = the IDE device name of your CF card (check with hdparm
        -i /dev/hdX) - some adapters, particularly USB, may show up under SCSI
        emulation as /dev/sdX.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Ignore the warning about trailing garbage - it's
        because of the digital signature.</emphasis></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Installing the standard PC by CDROM</title>

      <para>If you are installing to a standard PC using a CDROM and floppy
      disk, you will need to write the bootable CDROM and format the floppy
      disk.</para>

      <para>Installation on a standard PC with the CD-ROM (+ floppy disk)
      version requires the following steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>download the ISO image</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>burn the ISO image onto a CD-R (or -RW)</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">FreeBSD</emphasis> (ATAPI recorder):
          burncd -s max -e data cdrom-xxx.iso fixate</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows</emphasis>: use your favorite
          burning program (e.g. Nero) to record the ISO image (2048
          bytes/sector, Mode-1)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>take a standard 1.44 MB diskette or a USB flash drive
          (m0n0wall 1.3b only) and format it (with an MS-DOS/FAT file
          system!)</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>1.44 MB floppy disk</para>

              <para><emphasis role="bold">FreeBSD</emphasis>: fdformat -f 1440
              /dev/fd0 &amp;&amp; newfs_msdos -L "m0n0wallcfg" -f 1440
              /dev/fd0 Note: you can omit the fdformat step if the floppy disk
              is already (low-level) formatted</para>

              <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows</emphasis>: format A:</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>USB flash drive</para>

              <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows</emphasis>: use Windows
              Explorer to format the drive (FAT32)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>plug the PC into the network (LAN/WAN/...).</para>

          <caution>
            <para>If you have an existing DHCP server, and/or wish to use a
            different IP subnet on your LAN, you will need to first connect
            via the PC's keyboard/ monitor or serial console interface as
            described in the Initial Configuration chapter.</para>
          </caution>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>power up your PC, enter the BIOS and make sure that booting
          from CD-ROM is enabled and booting from floppy disk is
          disabled</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>insert CD-ROM and floppy disk (do not write-protect the floppy
          disk!)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>continue the boot process</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Now that your system has booted using the m0n0wall software
      continue to the section <xref linkend="setup-finalprep" />.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="setup-finalprep">
    <?dbhtml filename="setup-finalprep.html"?>

    <title>Final Preparation</title>

    <para>Now put your written Hard disk/ CF card or CDROM into your PC system
    and boot from it as described above. There are 3 ways to verify that the
    installation has completed successfully. Afterwards you can continue to
    the final steps below.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If your computer has a video screen you should see text output
        to the screen during the bootup and finally a text prompt blinking and
        waiting for you to start the configuration</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can try to access the m0n0wall from a client computer on the
        same network</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can try accessing the m0n0wall using a serial console
        connection</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <caution>
      <para>Since PCI Ethernet cards can be installed in various
      configurations, you may need to test which interface is actually being
      used as the LAN interface.</para>
    </caution>

    <para>These final steps will assign functions to the interfaces and change
    the LAN IP address as needed.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Wait for the console menu to appear, select 1. (assign network
        ports)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Assign functions (LAN/WAN/OPT) to your interfaces (hint: use
        auto-detection, or let the MAC addresses tell you which card is which
        one)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Change the LAN IP address, or use the default (192.168.1.1;
        m0n0wall acts as a DHCP server by default)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Access the webGUI (user: 'admin', default password:
        'mono')</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make the necessary changes to the default configuration</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <sect2>
      <title>Plugging in the Network Interfaces</title>

      <para>Plug the LAN interface into the hub or switch that is connected to
      your LAN. Plug the WAN interface into your Internet connection (DSL or
      cable modem, router, etc.) Additional Network interfaces can optionally
      be connected to other routers, hubs or an Ethernet capable
      device.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>If your Ethernet devices have built-in LEDs to show
        connectivity, verify that connected links are showing a green LED when
        the devices are physically powered on. If it is not showing green then
        there may be a problem with the cable (damaged or wiring) or with one
        of the Ethernet interfaces.</para>
      </tip>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>