<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Getting and Installing m0n0wall</title>
  <?dbhtml filename="setup.html"?>

  <sect1 id="Setup.ChoosingMedia">
     <?dbhtml filename="setup-choosingmedia.html"?>
     <title>Choosing your Media</title>

     <para>m0n0wall provides two options for PC users, 
	either a CD and floppy setup or a hard disk 
	setup.  
     </para>

     <sect2>
	<title>CD/floppy Setup</title>
	
	<para>m0n0wall can run from a CD, with a floppy 
	disk to save the configuration.  This is typically 
	a good way to try m0n0wall without actually overwriting
	a hard drive.  However, we do not recommend it for 
	production use, due to the likelihood of floppy disk or 
	drive failure.  A hard drive is far more reliable, and 
	Compact Flash is even more reliable still.
	</para>
     </sect2>

     <sect2>
	<title>Hard drive Setup</title>
	
	<para>You can install m0n0wall to any hard drive of 
	sufficient size (&gt;=8 MB, so basically any IDE hard drive
	ever made).  </para>

	<para>Of preference to many m0n0wall PC users for 
	maximum reliability is a Compact Flash to IDE adapter, 
	and a CF card.  </para>

      </sect2>

  </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="Setup.Installing">
     <?dbhtml filename="setup-installing.html"?>

     <title id="Setup.Installing.title">Getting and Installing the Software</title>

    <para>To download the PC image or CD, point your web browser
    to <ulink
    url="http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/downloads.php">http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/downloads.php</ulink>
    and select the WRAP download link from that page. Download the file
    to the machine from which you will be writing to the CompactFlash card.
    </para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Preparing the CompactFlash</title>

       <para>FIXME - add tutorial</para>

       <para>Now you need to write the image to a sufficiently large
       CF card (at least 8 MB). Extra space on the CF card is
       ignored; there is
       no benefit to using one larger than 8 MB other than possibly
       compatibility on future releases.</para>

        <para>The following sections will cover how to write the CF
        card in Windows, FreeBSD, and Linux.  </para>

        <sect3>
            <title>Windows</title>
            
            <para>Manuel Kasper's (author of m0n0wall) physdiskwrite should
            be used on Windows to write the CF card.  Download it from the
            m0n0wall web site's <ulink url="http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/physdiskwrite.php">
            physdiskwrite page</ulink>. </para>
            
            <para>Save physdiskwrite.exe and the downloaded m0n0wall image in
            the same directory on your hard drive, then open a Windows Command Prompt
            (click Start, Run, type in cmd and click OK).</para>
            
            <para>Plug in your CF card reader/writer and insert your CF card.</para>
            
            <para>'cd' into the directory containing physdiskwrite and the m0n0wall
            image and run the following:</para>
            
            <programlisting>physdiskwrite wrap-xxx.img</programlisting>

            <para>Replacing wrap-xxx.img with the name of the WRAP image you
            downloaded.</para>
              
            <para>You will see output similar to the following:</para>
            
              <programlisting>
physdiskwrite v0.5 by Manuel Kasper &lt;mk@neon1.net&gt;

Searching for physical drives...

Information for \\.\PhysicalDrive0:
   Windows:       cyl: 14593
                  tpc: 255
                  spt: 63
   C/H/S:         16383/16/63
   Model:         ST3120026A
   Serial number: 3JT1V2FS
   Firmware rev.: 3.06

Information for \\.\PhysicalDrive1:
   Windows:       cyl: 1
                  tpc: 255
                  spt: 63</programlisting>
              
            <para>You will see all the hard drives in your system listed, as well as
            the compact flash card.  Since we did not run <emphasis>
            physdiskwrite -u</emphasis>, physdiskwrite will refuse to write to any
            drive over 800
            MB.  This is a protection so you don't accidentally overwrite your hard drive.
            </para>

        </sect3>

        <sect3>
            <title>FreeBSD</title>

            <para>The procedures to image a CompactFlash card depend upon the
            type of adapter you are using. The CF card will either appear as
            a SCSI or IDE hard drive.</para>
            
            <para>Run the command <emphasis role="bold">atacontrol list</emphasis>.
            You will get output similar to the following:</para>

            <literallayout class="monospaced">
su-3.00# atacontrol list
ATA channel 0:
Master: ad0 &lt;WDC WD200EB-75CSF0/04.01B04&gt; ATA/ATAPI revision 5
Slave: ad1 &lt;WDC WD800AB-22CBA0/03.06A03&gt; ATA/ATAPI revision 5
ATA channel 1:
Master: acd0 &lt;_NEC CD-RW NR-7800A/10DA&gt; ATA/ATAPI revision 0
Slave: no device present
            </literallayout>

            <para>Then run the command <emphasis role="bold">camcontrol devlist</emphasis>.
            You will see output similar to the following:</para>
            
            <literallayout class="monospaced">
su-2.05b# camcontrol devlist
&lt;ADAPTEC RAID-5 320R&gt; at scbus2 target 0 lun 0 (pass0,da0)
&lt;SEAGATE ST39204LC 0005&gt; at scbus2 target 3 lun 0 (pass1,da1)
&lt;ESG-SHV SCA HSBP M10 0.05&gt; at scbus2 target 6 lun 0 (pass2)                
            </literallayout>

            <para>You will find your CF card somewhere in the
            above output.  Make note of its device name (adX or daX).
            </para>
            
            <para>Run the following command, replacing adX with your CF
            device as determined above, and wrap-xxx.img with the name
            of the m0n0wall image you downloaded.</para>
            
            <computeroutput>gzcat wrap-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/adX bs=16k</computeroutput>

              <para><emphasis>Ignore the warning about trailing garbage - it's
              because of the digital signature.</emphasis></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
              <title>Linux</title>

              <programlisting>gunzip -c net45xx-xxx.img | dd of=/dev/hdX bs=16k</programlisting>

              <para>where X = the IDE device name of your CF card 
              (check with hdparm -i /dev/hdX) - some adapters, particularly
              USB, may show up under SCSI emulation as /dev/sdX.</para>

              <para><emphasis>Ignore the warning about trailing garbage - it's
              because of the digital signature.</emphasis></para>
            
        </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="setup-finalprep.html"?>
    <title>Final Preparation</title>
    
    <para>Now put your written CF card into your WRAP board, and put it in its case.
    </para>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Plugging in the Network Interfaces</title>
        
        <para>The LAN and WAN interfaces are pre-assigned on the WRAP image.  
        </para>
        
        <sect3>
            <title>Two Ethernet models</title>
            
            <para>On the two Ethernet port models, the LAN port is the port
            closest to where the power adapter plugs in, and the WAN port is
            the port closest to the serial port.</para>
            
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/wrap-2nic.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            
        </sect3>
        
        <sect3>
            <title>Three Ethernet models</title>
            
            <para>On three Ethernet port WRAP models, the LAN port is the
            port closest to where the power adapter plugs in, and the WAN
            port is the middle port.</para>
            
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/wrap-3nic.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            
        </sect3>
            
        <para>Plug the LAN interface into the hub or switch that is connected
        to your LAN.  Plug the WAN interface into your Internet connection (DSL
        or cable modem, router, etc.)</para>
        
        <para>After plugging in your interfaces, plug in your WRAP to turn
        it on.</para>
        
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
</chapter>

