<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="Client.Machine.Config">
  <?dbhtml filename="clientconfigure.html"?>

  <title>Client Machine Configuration</title>

  <para>Now you need to get one of your client machines configured so you can
  access the webGUI to finish the configuration. A client machine is any
  Ethernet device (such as a computer, network printer or scanner, network
  camera...) that is connected to the LAN network of the m0n0wall PC. These
  devices will use the m0n0wall PC to reach the Internet and they will be
  protected by your m0n0wall configuration.</para>

  <para>If you are using the DHCP server built-into the m0n0wall system, these
  client machines will be receiving all of their IP configuration from the
  Soekris system running m0n0wall, even if they are not expected to connect to
  the Internet.</para>

  <tip>
    <para>If you have any servers in your LAN network such as a file or print
    server, you will want them to have fixed, non-changing IP addresses.
    Either assign them a fixed DHCP address or a static IP address.</para>
  </tip>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="clientconfigure-dhcp.html"?>

    <title>Using DHCP for client machines</title>

    <para>If you aren't familiar with networking, the easiest thing to do is
    set all your client machines to obtain their IP address from DHCP.
    m0n0wall enables its DHCP server on the LAN interface by default.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>LAN with m0n0wall as DHCP Server</title>

      <para>If you are going to use your m0n0wall as a DHCP server, set the
      client computer you will be using to access the webGUI to obtain its IP
      address using DHCP. Then release and renew your DHCP lease and you will
      get a lease from m0n0wall. The procedures to release and renew vary by
      the client machine's operating system, but if you don't know how to do
      this, a reboot of the client computer will achieve the same
      result.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>LAN with Existing DHCP Server</title>

      <para>If you have an existing DHCP server on your LAN, you just need to
      set your m0n0wall's LAN IP address as the default gateway address
      assigned by your DHCP server. This is because your LAN traffic is
      expected to be going through the LAN interface of your m0n0wall PC so
      that m0n0wall can protect your network traffic.</para>

      <para>When you get into the webGUI, you'll need to disable m0n0wall's
      DHCP server. You can also disable it from the console <link
      linkend="Connecting.Serial.Console">as described in the last
      chapter</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="clientconfigure-static.html"?>

    <title>Static IP addresses for client machines</title>

    <para>If you want to use a static IP address on your client machines, be
    sure to configure them in the same subnet as your m0n0wall LAN interface,
    using the appropriate DNS servers and the m0n0wall LAN IP address as the
    default gateway.</para>

    <para>We recommend you stick with DHCP at least initially to reduce the
    likelihood of problems.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>