<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: intro.xml,v 1.8 2005/09/25 23:32:29 chris Exp $ -->
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="intro.html"?>

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Features</title>

    <para>m0n0wall is a project aimed at creating a complete, embedded
    firewall software package that, when used together with an embedded
    computer platform like a <ulink url="???">Soekris</ulink> device, provides
    all the important features of commercial firewall boxes (including ease of
    use) at a fraction of the price (free software). m0n0wall is based on a
    bare-bones version of FreeBSD, along with a web server, PHP and a few
    other utilities. The entire system configuration is stored in one single
    XML text file to keep things transparent.</para>

    <para>m0n0wall is probably the first UNIX system that has its boot-time
    configuration done with PHP, rather than the usual shell scripts, and that
    has the entire system configuration stored in XML format.</para>

    <para>m0n0wall already provides many of the features of expensive
    commercial firewalls, including:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>web interface (supports SSL)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>serial console interface for recovery</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>set LAN IP address</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>reset password</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>restore factory defaults</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>reboot system</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>wireless support (access point with PRISM-II/2.5/3 cards,
        BSS/IBSS with other cards including Cisco)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>captive portal</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>802.1Q VLAN support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>stateful packet filtering</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>block/pass rules</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>logging</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT/PAT (including 1:1)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DHCP client, PPPoE, PPTP and Telstra BigPond Cable support on
        the WAN interface</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IPsec VPN tunnels (IKE; with support for hardware crypto cards,
        mobile clients and certificates)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PPTP VPN (with RADIUS server support)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>static routes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DHCP server and relay</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>caching DNS forwarder</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DynDNS client and RFC 2136 DNS updater</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SNMP agent</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>traffic shaper</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SVG-based traffic grapher</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>firmware upgrade through the web browser</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Wake on LAN client</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>configuration backup/restore</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>host/network aliases</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Getting Started with m0n0wall on the Soekris</title>

    <para>The m0n0wall Quick Start Guide is intended to get m0n0wall up and
    running on a Soekris embedded computer system. There will be descriptions
    on configuring two interfaces (LAN and WAN) setup. The <ulink
    url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/handbook/">m0n0wall Handbook</ulink> contains the
    information you need to further configure your m0n0wall installation after
    completing this guide.</para>

    <para>This version of the Quick Start Guide is specifically tailored to
    the <ulink url="http://soekris.com/">Soekris</ulink> platforms. If you are
    using WRAP or the newer ALIX hardware from <ulink
    url="http://www.pcengines.ch">PC Engines</ulink>, please see the <ulink
    url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/quickstartwrap/"> WRAP/ALIX Quick Start
    Guide</ulink> and for PC hardware, please see the <ulink
    url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/quickstartpc/">PC Quick Start
    Guide</ulink>.</para>

    <para>There are a number of example configurations in <ulink
    url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/handbook/examples.html">Chapter 9</ulink> of the
    <ulink url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/handbook/">m0n0wall Handbook</ulink>. These
    configurations describe how to configure several things such as multiple
    LAN interfaces, setting up DMZ interfaces, wireless interfaces, etc. The
    base for adding those additional features will be the basic LAN/WAN setup
    this guide describes.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Why use an embedded system?</title>

      <para>Below are some reasons you might chose to use an embedded system
      instead of a PC.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Small size</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Low power consumption</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No moving parts (or very few)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom boxes/ enclosures available to present a professional
          look or to place outdoors</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-prerequisites.html"?>

    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>This section will go through the hardware and network information
    you need to gather to proceed through in this guide.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Required Hardware</title>

      <para>First, you need to make sure you have the following
      hardware.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Soekris board</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Soekris case</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Soekris power adapter</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compact Flash card at least 16 MB in size (8 for m0n0wall 1.2
          and earlier)</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>for best reliability, use a recognized brand, such as
              SanDisk</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>one user also reported that Dane-Elec Compact Flash cards
              fail to work properly in net45xx systems</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compact Flash card reader/writer for another computer to
          install the software</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Two network cables</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Required Network Information</title>

      <para>You'll need some information about your Internet connection.
      You'll need to know which category of the below list your Internet
      connection falls into, and the appropriate details. You can usually find
      these details on your ISP's website, and/or in paperwork you receive
      when you sign up for service. You can also call your ISP's technical
      support to get this information.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Static IP</emphasis></para>

          <para>- If you have a connection with a static IP, you will need to
          make note of your IP address, subnet mask, default gateway, and DNS
          server IP's.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">DHCP</emphasis></para>

          <para>- If you have an Internet connection that uses DHCP, you need
          not gather any more information unless your ISP requires you to pass
          a certain DHCP hostname value (this is uncommon). If this is the
          case, you will need to check with your ISP to determine this
          hostname.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">PPPoE</emphasis></para>

          <para>- Many DSL providers provide PPPoE or PPPoA service. Either of
          these is supported with the PPPoE WAN option. You will need to know
          your PPPoE username and password and possibly your service name
          (though this can usually be left blank).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">PPTP</emphasis></para>

          <para>- A few ISP's require you to connect to them via PPTP. If your
          ISP requires this, you will need a username, password, local IP
          address, and remote IP address from your ISP.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">BigPond</emphasis></para>

          <para>- This setting is for BigPond cable connections. You will need
          your username, password, and possibly authentication server and
          domain.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You will also need to know if you are connected directly to the
      Internet or if you are behind a modem or other device that is connected
      to the Internet. For example, maybe your Internet connection uses PPPoE
      but you have a PPPoE modem that receives the IP address from your
      Internet provider and then offers those network services to your
      internal network using DHCP or static IP.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>The instructions for using the m0n0wall device are written with
        the idea that your m0n0wall has direct access to the Internet. If you
        have another device between your m0n0wall and the Internet that offers
        security or otherwise affects the network traffic (such as a proxy
        service, NAT device or port use limitations by your Internet provider)
        the configuration instructions and troubleshooting may not apply to
        your case.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>Make note of the appropriate information for your connection type
      for later use.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Be sure that you write down all of your existing Internet
        configuration BEFORE making changes to use your m0n0wall device. Once
        you have disconnected yourself from the Internet you will lose access
        to the numerous online help sources until you have re-established your
        connection.</para>
      </important>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-choosing.html"?>

    <title>Choosing Your Soekris Hardware</title>

    <para>The Soekris hardware you choose will depend on what features you
    will use, how much bandwidth you have, and any add on devices that you
    wish to use. Since m0n0wall is based on FreeBSD 4, most hardware that
    works with FreeBSD also works with m0n0wall. See the <ulink
    url="http://www.freebsd.org/releases/4.11R/hardware-i386.html">FreeBSD/i386
    Hardware Notes</ulink> for a detailed listing of supported
    hardware.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>If you buy a Soerkis system on the Internet (for example from
      eBay) you may have received a customized board that has limited
      features. Some things to look out for are missing Ethernet connections,
      less onboard memory or maybe a missing PCI interface.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>Below is a list of some common Soerkis versions:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>net4501-30: 133 Mhz CPU, 64 Mbyte SDRAM, 3 Ethernet, 2 Serial,
        CF socket, 1 Mini-PCI socket, 3.3V PCI connector</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>net4801-60: 266 Mhz CPU, 256 Mbyte SDRAM, 3 Ethernet, 2 serial,
        USB connector, CF socket, 44 pins IDE connector, 1 Mini-PCI socket,
        3.3V PCI connector.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>net5501-70, 500 Mhz CPU, 512 Mbyte DDR-SDRAM, 4 Ethernet, 2
        Serial, USB connector, CF socket, 44 pins IDE connector, SATA
        connector, 1 Mini-PCI socket, 3.3V PCI connector.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Some add on devices for Soekris hardware might be:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>lan1621 board x2 port ethernet board</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>lan1641 board x4 port ethernet board</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>vpn accelerator card</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>wireless mini-pci card (A/B/G)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>The m0n0wall 1.3 releases are based on FreeBSD 6.2-RELEASE. The
      <ulink
      url="http://www.freebsd.org/releases/6.2R/hardware-i386.html">Hardware
      Notes</ulink> for this version is different than the older FreeBSD 4.x
      versions.</para>
    </note>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Processor</emphasis></para>

    <para>For most broadband connections, any 100MHz or faster processor will
    be sufficient. For example, if you have less than 10 Mb of Internet
    bandwidth (combined upload and download speed), an embedded device like
    the WRAP or Soekris platforms will suffice. For 10 Mb up to a full T3 or
    more, a 500MHz system like the newer Soekris, ALIX, or embedded device
    like a NexCom is more appropriate. See Chapter 2 of the Users Guide for
    further details on compatible hardware.</para>

    <para>For connections faster than a T3 using many VPN sessions, you will
    likely want to use a customized version of m0n0wall specifically built for
    your requirements, and high end Pentium 4, Xeon, or similar hardware. This
    is beyond the scope of this document.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">RAM</emphasis></para>

    <para>We recommend an embedded system with at least 64 MB of RAM. More
    memory is particularly useful for VPN connections. Hard drive or CF
    installs are not recommended with less than 64 MB RAM because you will
    probably run out of RAM during upgrades and m0n0wall has no swap, so the
    upgrade will fail.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Hardware Sizing</emphasis></para>

    <para>Keep in mind there is no standard "if you have X Internet connection
    and Y number of machines on your network, then you need Z hardware". It
    varies depending on what services you will use, and your Internet traffic
    characteristics. The one thing that will require significantly more CPU,
    and/or a VPN accelerator card, is if you'll require more than a couple
    Mbps of VPN traffic for extended periods.</para>

    <para>Some examples of non-encrypted network throughput can be found
    below, when using the default configuration. Please note that some of
    these results were reported by users and not officially tested by a
    developer of the m0n0wall code. Additional information can be found on
    <ulink
    url="http://m0n0.ch/wall/docbook/faq-performancespecifications.html">this
    FAQ entry.</ulink></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Soekris net4501, WAN &lt;-&gt; LAN TCP throughput of about 17
        Mbps, including NAT</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Soekris net4801, throughput in excess of 50 Mbps</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PC Engines ALIX.1, throughput in excess of 90 Mbps</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Soekris net5501-70 500Mhz 512M RAM, 84 Mbps</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Liantec 5842 with OpenBSD 4.0, 395Mbps</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>New standard PCs, &gt; 100 Mbps (depending on Ethernet cards
        used)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sempron 2800+ (1.6GHz) using Intel Pro 1000 PT pci-e card,
        760Mbps</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sempron 2800+ (1.6GHz) using Intel Pro 1000 GT pci card,
        400Mbps</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Some encryption speeds are shown below. Please note that speed will
    change based on the number of concurrent connections and the type of
    encryption being used.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Soekris net4801, 3DES-MD5 IPSec encryption, 3.5Mb/s</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Cards</emphasis></para>

    <para>You will need at least two network interfaces in the hardware you
    are using. If the Soekris system that you have selected has a PCI
    interface you can add an additional PCI based ethernet card. Most any PCI
    based cards are compatible with m0n0wall but be sure that whatever card
    you use has been tested with the Soekris system, check the <ulink
    url="http://m0n0.ch/wall/docbook/hardware-ethernet.html">Users
    Guide</ulink> for further details.</para>

    <para>For this document, we will assume there are two Ethernet interfaces.
    You can have additional interfaces installed in the system, but do not
    configure them during these quick installation procedures. Documentation
    in the Users Guide will soon be available to assist you in setting up
    additional LAN interfaces, DMZ interfaces, wireless setups, etc.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>You should write down the MAC hardware addresses of each Ethernet
      interface if possible. During the configuration of m0n0wall, the
      Ethernet interfaces will be identified by these addresses. If you do not
      know them in advance you may need to do some tests to find out which
      network card has been selected for the LAN and which network has been
      selected for the WAN. MAC addresses look like 00:1c:b3:bb:80:42.</para>
    </tip>

    <sect2>
      <title>Storage Medium</title>

      <para>m0n0wall will run off of a Compact Flash card or a hard drive. In
      most cases you will use a Compact Flash card with the PC Engines
      embedded systems but some of these systems support IDE or SATA drives.
      The pros and cons of each follow. Although you can choose the one most
      appropriate for your situation, the rest of this Quick Start guide will
      assume that you are using a Compact Flash card. Both Compact Flash and
      hard drive installations are remotely upgradeable via the webGUI.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">CompactFlash</emphasis></para>

      <para>CompactFlash (CF) is a good choice for most any deployment. CF
      cards are more reliable than hard drives and the floppy drives that hold
      the configuration in the CD/floppy setup, and are remotely upgradeable
      via the webGUI. The downside is you might spend more money getting a CF
      setup working. If you are not using an embedded device with an onboard
      CF adapter, you will have to spend about $10 USD on a IDE to CF adapter.
      You'll need to purchase a CF card at least 16 MB in size.</para>

      <para>I purchase used 16 MB CF cards off eBay to use for m0n0wall
      installations, and get them for $5-$10 USD each. You may also need a CF
      reader on your PC to write the m0n0wall image to the CF card. Those are
      approximately $30 USD. So you could be looking at a total expenditure of
      about $50 USD. But most any business environment should be able to
      justify such a small expenditure for the increase in reliability.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Hard Drive</emphasis></para>

      <para>Hard drives are readily available but most embedded systems will
      not support them. The likelihood of a hard drive failure is pretty high,
      given that the hardware being used is likely old. They can also get very
      warm with high disk activity and since the embedded systems discussed
      here do not include ventilation, this might be important in your
      choice.</para>

      <para>If you have an extra IDE interface you can still use it with an
      IDE to CompactFlash adapter. Such an adapter can be purchased new for
      about $10 USD. <ulink
      url="         http://www.pcengines.ch/cflash.htm">PC Engines</ulink>
      sells them, amongst other vendors.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-CIDR.html"?>

    <title>Understanding CIDR Subnet Mask Notation</title>

    <para>m0n0wall uses a subnet mask format that you may not be familiar
    with. Rather than the common 255.x.x.x, it uses CIDR (Classless
    InterDomain Routing) notation.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>CIDR Table</title>

      <para>You can refer to the following table to find the CIDR equivalent
      of your subnet mask.</para>

      <table>
        <title>CIDR Subnet Table</title>

        <tgroup cols="5">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Subnet Mask</entry>

              <entry>CIDR Prefix</entry>

              <entry>Total IP's</entry>

              <entry>Usable IP's</entry>

              <entry>Number of Class C networks</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.255</entry>

              <entry>/32</entry>

              <entry>1</entry>

              <entry>1</entry>

              <entry>1/256th</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.254</entry>

              <entry>/31</entry>

              <entry>2</entry>

              <entry>0</entry>

              <entry>1/128th</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.252</entry>

              <entry>/30</entry>

              <entry>4</entry>

              <entry>2</entry>

              <entry>1/64th</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.248</entry>

              <entry>/29</entry>

              <entry>8</entry>

              <entry>6</entry>

              <entry>1/32nd</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.240</entry>

              <entry>/28</entry>

              <entry>16</entry>

              <entry>14</entry>

              <entry>1/16th</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.224</entry>

              <entry>/27</entry>

              <entry>32</entry>

              <entry>30</entry>

              <entry>1/8th</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.192</entry>

              <entry>/26</entry>

              <entry>64</entry>

              <entry>62</entry>

              <entry>1/4th</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.128</entry>

              <entry>/25</entry>

              <entry>128</entry>

              <entry>126</entry>

              <entry>1 half</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.255.0</entry>

              <entry>/24</entry>

              <entry>256</entry>

              <entry>254</entry>

              <entry>1</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.254.0</entry>

              <entry>/23</entry>

              <entry>512</entry>

              <entry>510</entry>

              <entry>2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.252.0</entry>

              <entry>/22</entry>

              <entry>1024</entry>

              <entry>1022</entry>

              <entry>4</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.248.0</entry>

              <entry>/21</entry>

              <entry>2048</entry>

              <entry>2046</entry>

              <entry>8</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.240.0</entry>

              <entry>/20</entry>

              <entry>4096</entry>

              <entry>4094</entry>

              <entry>16</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.224.0</entry>

              <entry>/19</entry>

              <entry>8192</entry>

              <entry>8190</entry>

              <entry>32</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.192.0</entry>

              <entry>/18</entry>

              <entry>16,384</entry>

              <entry>16,382</entry>

              <entry>64</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.128.0</entry>

              <entry>/17</entry>

              <entry>32,768</entry>

              <entry>32,766</entry>

              <entry>128</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.255.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/16</entry>

              <entry>65,536</entry>

              <entry>65,534</entry>

              <entry>256</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.254.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/15</entry>

              <entry>131,072</entry>

              <entry>131,070</entry>

              <entry>512</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.252.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/14</entry>

              <entry>262,144</entry>

              <entry>262,142</entry>

              <entry>1024</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.248.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/13</entry>

              <entry>524,288</entry>

              <entry>524,286</entry>

              <entry>2048</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.240.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/12</entry>

              <entry>1,048,576</entry>

              <entry>1,048,574</entry>

              <entry>4096</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.224.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/11</entry>

              <entry>2,097,152</entry>

              <entry>2,097,150</entry>

              <entry>8192</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.192.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/10</entry>

              <entry>4,194,304</entry>

              <entry>4,194,302</entry>

              <entry>16,384</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.128.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/9</entry>

              <entry>8,388,608</entry>

              <entry>8,388,606</entry>

              <entry>32,768</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>255.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/8</entry>

              <entry>16,777,216</entry>

              <entry>16,777,214</entry>

              <entry>65,536</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>254.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/7</entry>

              <entry>33,554,432</entry>

              <entry>33,554,430</entry>

              <entry>131,072</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>252.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/6</entry>

              <entry>67,108,864</entry>

              <entry>67,108,862</entry>

              <entry>262,144</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>248.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/5</entry>

              <entry>134,217,728</entry>

              <entry>134,217,726</entry>

              <entry>1,048,576</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>240.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/4</entry>

              <entry>268,435,456</entry>

              <entry>268,435,454</entry>

              <entry>2,097,152</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>224.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/3</entry>

              <entry>536,870,912</entry>

              <entry>536,870,910</entry>

              <entry>4,194,304</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>192.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/2</entry>

              <entry>1,073,741,824</entry>

              <entry>1,073,741,822</entry>

              <entry>8,388,608</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>128.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/1</entry>

              <entry>2,147,483,648</entry>

              <entry>2,147,483,646</entry>

              <entry>16,777,216</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>0.0.0.0</entry>

              <entry>/0</entry>

              <entry>4,294,967,296</entry>

              <entry>4,294,967,294</entry>

              <entry>33,554,432</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>So where do these CIDR numbers come from anyway?</title>

      <para>The CIDR number comes from the number of 1's in the subnet mask
      when converted to binary.</para>

      <para>The common subnet mask 255.255.255.0 is
      11111111.11111111.11111111.00000000 in binary. This adds up to 24 1's,
      or /24 (pronounced 'slash twenty four').</para>

      <para>A subnet mask of 255.255.255.192 is
      11111111.11111111.11111111.11000000 in binary, or 26 1's, hence a
      /26.</para>

      <para>And so on...</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>