<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="captiveportal.html"?>

  <title>Captive Portal</title>

  <para>This Captive Portal functionality allows you to control HTTP browser
  access to the Internet. All users trying to leave the selected network (for
  example all users from the LAN network going to the Internet) will be
  redirected to a HTML page stored on your m0n0wall. This page is typically
  where the user trying to reach the Internet can enter in username and
  password information to be authenticated and allowed access to the
  Internet.</para>

  <para>Users are identified by their MAC hardware address of their ethernet
  card. All traffic trying to reach the Internet or selected network by any
  user is blocked until they use a web browser and finish the authentication
  process on the HTML authentication page.</para>

  <para>Some features of the m0n0wall Captive Portal include:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Interface selection (typically the LAN interface)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Allow selected IP or MAC addresses</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>User authentication choices (none, local, or RADIUS)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Maximum concurrent connections</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Concurrent user logins</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Local user management option</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Per user bandwidth restrictions</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Idle and Hard timeout</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Log out popup window</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Redirection URL</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>MAC filtering</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>HTTPS authentication</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Customizable portal page contents</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Customizable authentication failure page</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Voucher support (in the upcoming 1.3 m0n0wall)</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <caution>
    <para>Don't forget to enable the DHCP server on your captive portal
    interface! Make sure that the default/maximum DHCP lease time is higher
    than the timeout entered on this page. Also, the DNS forwarder needs to be
    enabled for DNS lookups by unauthenticated clients to work.</para>
  </caution>

  <sect1>
    <title>Connection Management</title>

    <para>Below are some of the Connection options that can be configured for
    use with the Captive Portal. Additionally there is some information about
    allowing pass-through MAC addresses and making a list of allowed IP
    addresses that do not need authentication.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Connection Parameters</title>

      <tgroup cols="2" tgroupstyle="Format D">
        <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

        <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2*" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">Parameter</entry>

            <entry valign="top">Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Interface</entry>

            <entry>Choose which interface to run the captive portal on.
            Captive Portal can only be run on one interface.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Maximum concurrent connections</entry>

            <entry>This setting limits the number of concurrent connections to
            the captive portal HTTP(S) server. This does not set how many
            users can be logged in to the captive portal, but rather how many
            users can load the portal page or authenticate at the same time!
            Default is 4 connections per client IP address, with a total
            maximum of 16 connections.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Idle timeout</entry>

            <entry>Clients will be disconnected after this amount of
            inactivity. They may log in again immediately, though. Leave this
            field blank for no idle timeout.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Hard timeout</entry>

            <entry>Clients will be disconnected after this amount of time,
            regardless of activity. They may log in again immediately, though.
            Leave this field blank for no hard timeout (not recommended unless
            an idle timeout is set).</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Logout popup window</entry>

            <entry>If enabled, a popup window will appear when clients are
            allowed through the captive portal. This allows clients to
            explicitly disconnect themselves before the idle or hard timeout
            occurs.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Redirection URL</entry>

            <entry>If you provide a URL here, clients will be redirected to
            that URL instead of the one they initially tried to access after
            they've authenticated.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Concurrent user logins</entry>

            <entry>If this option is set, only the most recent login per
            username will be active. Subsequent logins will cause machines
            previously logged in with the same username to be
            disconnected.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>MAC filtering</entry>

            <entry>If this option is set, no attempts will be made to ensure
            that the MAC address of clients stays the same while they're
            logged in. This is required when the MAC address of the client
            cannot be determined (usually because there are routers between
            m0n0wall and the clients).</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Per-user bandwidth restriction</entry>

            <entry>If this option is set, the captive portal will restrict
            each user who logs in to the specified default bandwidth. RADIUS
            can override the default settings. Leave empty or set to 0 for no
            limit. <emphasis role="bold">You will need to enable the traffic
            shaper for this to be effective.</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <sect2>
      <title>Pass-through MAC Addresses</title>

      <para>Adding MAC addresses as pass-through MACs allows them access
      through the captive portal automatically without being taken to the
      portal page. The pass-through MACs can change their IP addresses on the
      fly and upon the next access, the pass-through tables are changed
      accordingly. Pass-through MACs will however still be disconnected after
      the captive portal timeout period.</para>

      <para>You can enter a list of MAC address (6 hex octets separated by
      colons) and a description here for your reference (it is not
      parsed).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Allowed IP Addresses</title>

      <para>Adding allowed IP addresses will allow IP access to/from these
      addresses through the captive portal without being taken to the portal
      page. This can be used for a web server serving images for the portal
      page or a DNS server on another network, for example. By specifying from
      addresses, it may be used to always allow pass-through access from a
      client behind the captive portal.</para>

      <para>Some sample rules are:</para>

      <para>any x.x.x.x &gt; All connections to the IP address are
      allowed</para>

      <para>x.x.x.x &gt; any All connections from the IP address are
      allowed</para>

      <para>For each entry on the Allowed IP Address list you can use
      <emphasis>From</emphasis> to always allow an IP address through the
      captive portal (without authentication). Use <emphasis>To</emphasis> to
      allow access from all clients (even non-authenticated ones) behind the
      portal to this IP address. Additionally each entry will contain an IP
      address and a description for your reference (it is not parsed).</para>

      <caution>
        <para>If you have servers such as web or email on a separate
        subnetwork (for example a DMZ) be sure to add their IP addresses to
        this list. Otherwise users will not be allowed to access them without
        authenticating first.</para>
      </caution>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Authentication Management</title>

    <para>There are 3 user management choices that can be used to authenticate
    users to the Captive Portal.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>No authentication</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Local user manager</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Radius authentication</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Optionally web authentication can be secured with HTTPS.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Secure Authentication</title>

      <para>Below are some of the Secure Authentication options that can be
      configured for use with th Captive Portal to .</para>

      <table>
        <title>Secure Authentication Parameters</title>

        <tgroup cols="2" tgroupstyle="Format D">
          <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">Parameter</entry>

              <entry valign="top">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>HTTPS login</entry>

              <entry>If enabled, the username and password will be transmitted
              over an HTTPS connection to protect against eavesdroppers. A
              server name, certificate and matching private key must also be
              specified below.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>HTTPS server name</entry>

              <entry>This name will be used in the form action for the HTTPS
              POST and should match the Common Name (CN) in your certificate
              (otherwise, the client browser will most likely display a
              security warning). Make sure captive portal clients can resolve
              this name in DNS.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>HTTPS certificate</entry>

              <entry>Paste a signed certificate in X.509 PEM format
              here.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>HTTPS private key</entry>

              <entry>Paste an RSA private key in PEM format here.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Local User Management</title>

      <para>When using the Local User Manager option for Authentication it is
      possible to store and access a list of users on the m0n0wall device
      itself. This list is manually entered from the web interface and
      includes the following parameters.</para>

      <table>
        <title>User Parameters</title>

        <tgroup cols="2" tgroupstyle="Format D">
          <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">Parameter</entry>

              <entry valign="top">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Username</entry>

              <entry>The name a user will use to authenticate with</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Password</entry>

              <entry>The password a user will use to authenticate with</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Fullname</entry>

              <entry>User's full name, for your own information only</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Expiration Date</entry>

              <entry>Leave blank if the account shouldn't expire, otherwise
              enter the expiration date in the following format:
              mm/dd/yyyy</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Radius User Management</title>

      <para>When using the Radius Authentication option for Authentication it
      is possible to authenticate with an existing Radius server on a
      connected network. The Radius server will manage the user authentication
      requests. This list is manually entered from the web interface and
      includes the following parameters.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Radius Server Parameters</title>

        <tgroup cols="2" tgroupstyle="Format D">
          <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">Parameter</entry>

              <entry valign="top">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Primary RADIUS server</entry>

              <entry>Enter the IP address of the RADIUS server which users of
              the captive portal have to authenticate against. You can change
              the default port (1812) and shared secret. Optionally leave the
              shared secret blank to not use a RADIUS shared secret (not
              recommended).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Secondary RADIUS server</entry>

              <entry>If you have a second RADIUS server, you can activate it
              by entering its IP address, port and shared secret as done for
              the primary server.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>send RADIUS accounting packets</entry>

              <entry>If this is enabled, RADIUS accounting packets will be
              sent to the primary RADIUS server. Optionally change the default
              port (1813).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Reauthentication</entry>

              <entry>If reauthentication is enabled, Access-Requests will be
              sent to the RADIUS server for each user that is logged in every
              minute. If an Access-Reject is received for a user, that user is
              disconnected from the captive portal immediately.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Accounting updates</entry>

              <entry>These reauthentication updates can be configured to
              support no accounting updates, stop/start accounting, or interim
              updates.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>RADIUS MAC authentication</entry>

              <entry>If this option is enabled, the captive portal will try to
              authenticate users by sending their MAC address as the username
              and a static password/secret to the RADIUS server.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>RADIUS Session-Timeout attributes</entry>

              <entry>When this is enabled, clients will be disconnected after
              the amount of time retrieved from the RADIUS Session-Timeout
              attribute.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Radius Type</entry>

              <entry>If RADIUS type is set to Cisco, in RADIUS requests
              (Authentication/Accounting) the value of Calling-Station-Id will
              be set to the client's IP address and the Called-Station-Id to
              the client's MAC address. Default behaviour is
              Calling-Station-Id = client's MAC address and Called-Station-Id
              = m0n0wall's WAN MAC address.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>MAC address format</entry>

              <entry>This option changes the MAC address format used in the
              whole RADIUS system. Change this if you also need to change the
              username format for RADIUS MAC authentication. default:
              00:11:22:33:44:55 singledash: 001122-334455 ietf:
              00-11-22-33-44-55 cisco: 0011.2233.4455 unformatted:
              001122334455</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Custom Pages And Files</title>

    <para>It is possible to customize the HTML pages that are used for the
    Captive portal authentication process. The page that does the
    authentication itself an be changed as well as the default page that is
    shown for a failed authentication. Graphics files can also be loaded into
    the m0n0wall device for use on these pages, up to a maximum of 256
    KB.</para>

    <para>Optionally a redirected URL can be used where clients will be
    redirected instead of the one they initially tried to access after they've
    authenticated. After reading this information they are free to access the
    remote networks since they have already been authenticated.</para>

    <para>Below are the parameters for custom pages and files.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Portal Page Contents</title>

      <para>Upload an HTML file for the portal page here (leave blank to keep
      the current one). Make sure to include a form (POST to
      "$PORTAL_ACTION$") with a submit button (name="accept") and a hidden
      field with name="redirurl" and value="$PORTAL_REDIRURL$". Include the
      "auth_user" and "auth_pass" input fields if authentication is enabled,
      otherwise it will always fail. Example code for the form:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;form method="post" action="$PORTAL_ACTION$"&gt;
   &lt;input name="auth_user" type="text"&gt;
   &lt;input name="auth_pass" type="password"&gt;
   &lt;input name="redirurl" type="hidden" value="$PORTAL_REDIRURL$"&gt;
   &lt;input name="accept" type="submit" value="Continue"&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Authentication Error Page Contents</title>

      <para>The contents of the HTML file that you upload here are displayed
      when an authentication error occurs. You may include "$PORTAL_MESSAGE$",
      which will be replaced by the error or reply messages from the RADIUS
      server, if any. You may also include a new login form in the error page
      to allow the user to attempt another login directly.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Custom Files</title>

      <para>The loading page for custom files can be found in the File Manager
      section of the Captive Portal main menu.</para>

      <para>Any files that you upload here will be made available in the root
      directory of the captive portal HTTP(S) server. You may reference them
      directly from your portal page HTML code using relative paths. Example:
      you've uploaded an image with the name 'test.jpg' using the file
      manager. Then you can include it in your portal page like this:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;img src="test.jpg" width=... height=...&gt; </programlisting>

      <para>The total size limit for all files is 256 KB.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Vouchers</title>

    <para>Below is a quick howto from mwiget who added the Voucher feature to
    m0n0wall.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Quick Howto</title>

      <para>To enable, create and manage voucher support via captive portal,
      there is a new Tab under Services-&gt;Captive Portal: Voucher.</para>

      <para>Enable captive portal first, upload a landing page that contains
      an input field 'auth_voucher'. An example can be found on the the URL
      above. Then enable Voucher support on the Voucher tab. Initially you can
      leave all fields with its defaults. Every new install will create unique
      encryption keys. </para>

      <para>Now add at least one "Roll" by clicking '+' on the Vouchers page,
      right to 'Voucher rolls': Specify a Roll Number, e.g. 0, how many
      vouchers that roll shall contain, and how long each voucher allows
      network access. Then generate the new vouchers by clicking on the paper
      logo right to the newly added roll. This will generate a CSV file and
      download via your browser.</para>

      <para>Each of these generated vouchers can now be used by users for the
      configured amount of minutes for that roll. Note that as soon as a
      voucher has been activated, its timer will run down to zero and then
      block access, no matter if the session is idle or got disconnected due
      to logout or session termination.</para>

      <para>To test the vouchers in the m0n0wall GUI, click on
      Status-&gt;Captive Portal. New tabs, dedicated to voucher handling, show
      up when voucher support is enabled. Click on status-&gt;captive
      portal-&gt; Test Vouchers and enter one or more of the newly generated
      vouchers from the downloaded CSV file and click submit. A message will
      be shown with the validation and duration of each given voucher.</para>

      <para>One can add multiple rolls, e.g. to have vouchers with different
      time credit. It is also possible, to enter multiple vouchers, separated
      by space, to gain the sum of time credit of all entered vouchers.
      </para>

      <para>There is more to it, read the comments to each config parameter on
      the voucher page. </para>

      <para>Note on the very short public/private RSA keys: I know, those can
      be cracked easy and in no time, if one of the keys is known. The idea
      here was to make it a little bit harder than simply adding a shared
      password into the m0n0wall config file. Unfortunately I'm no expert on
      encryption but I assume with such short encrypted vouchers, there is no
      security difference between the used RSA keys and a symmetric
      encryption. Anyhow, all that encryption/decryption stuff is done in a
      newly added binary C program voucher.c, that is compiled and added into
      the m0n0wall image, and can be modified to increase the usability and
      security. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Voucher Parameters</title>

      <para>Below are the following parameters that can be configured for
      voucher use in the upcoming 1.3 m0n0wall). The Enable Vouchers checkbox
      must activated for these parameters to be used.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Changing any Voucher parameter (apart from managing the list of
        Rolls) on this page will render existing vouchers useless if they were
        generated with different settings.</para>
      </note>

      <table>
        <title>Voucher Parameters</title>

        <tgroup cols="2" tgroupstyle="Format D">
          <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">Parameter</entry>

              <entry valign="top">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Voucher Rolls</entry>

              <entry>Create, generate and activate Rolls with Vouchers that
              allow access through the captive portal for the configured time.
              Once a voucher is activated, its clock is started and runs
              uninterrupted until it expires. During that time, the voucher
              can be re-used from the same or a different computer. If the
              voucher is used again from another computer, the previous
              session is stopped.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Voucher public key</entry>

              <entry>Paste an RSA public key (64 Bit or smaller) in PEM format
              here. This key is used to decrypt vouchers.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Voucher private key</entry>

              <entry>Paste an RSA private key (64 Bit or smaller) in PEM
              format here. This key is only used to generate encrypted
              vouchers and doesn't need to be available if the vouchers have
              been generated offline.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Character set</entry>

              <entry>Tickets are generated with the specified character set.
              It should contain printable characters (numbers, lower case and
              upper case letters) that are hard to confuse with others. Avoid
              e.g. 0/O and l/1.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry># of Roll Bits</entry>

              <entry>Reserves a range in each voucher to store the Roll# it
              belongs to. Allowed range: 1..31. Sum of Roll+Ticket+Checksum
              bits must be one Bit less than the RSA key size.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry># of Ticket Bits</entry>

              <entry>Reserves a range in each voucher to store the Ticket# it
              belongs to. Allowed range: 1..16. Using 16 bits allows a roll to
              have up to 65535 vouchers. A bit array, stored in RAM and in the
              config, is used to mark if a voucher has been used. A bit array
              for 65535 vouchers requires 8 KB of storage.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry># of Checksum Bits</entry>

              <entry>Reserves a range in each voucher to store a simple
              checksum over Roll# and Ticket#. Allowed range is 0..31.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Magic Number</entry>

              <entry>Magic number stored in every voucher. Verified during
              voucher check. Size depends on how many bits are left by
              Roll+Ticket+Checksum bits. If all bits are used, no magic number
              will be used and checked.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Save Interval</entry>

              <entry>The list of active and used vouchers can be stored in the
              system's configuration file once every x minutes to survive
              power outages. No save is done if no new vouchers have been
              activated. Enter 0 to never write runtime state to XML
              config.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Invalid Voucher Message</entry>

              <entry>Error message displayed for invalid vouchers on captive
              portal error page ($PORTAL_MESSAGE$)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Expired Voucher Message</entry>

              <entry>Error message displayed for expired vouchers on captive
              portal error page ($PORTAL_MESSAGE$).</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Voucher Rolls</title>

      <para>Each voucher roll has the following parameters.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Voucher Roll Parameters</title>

        <tgroup cols="2" tgroupstyle="Format D">
          <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">Parameter</entry>

              <entry valign="top">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Roll#</entry>

              <entry>Enter the Roll# (0..65535) found on top of the
              generated/printed vouchers.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Minutes per Ticket</entry>

              <entry>Defines the time in minutes that a user is allowed
              access. The clock starts ticking the first time a voucher is
              used for authentication.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Count</entry>

              <entry>Enter the number of vouchers (1..1023) found on top of
              the generated/printed vouchers. WARNING: Changing this number
              for an existing Roll will mark all vouchers as unused
              again.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Comment</entry>

              <entry>Can be used to further identify this roll. Ignored by the
              system.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Limitations</title>

    <para>Because users are identified by their MAC hardware address it is
    possible that someone using a packet sniffer can spoof/ impersonate the
    authenticated MAC hardware address and thereby gain network access.
    Setting a hard timeout can help to minimize this risk.</para>

    <para>Don't forget to enable the DHCP server on your captive portal
    interface! Make sure that the default/maximum DHCP lease time is higher
    than the timeout entered on this page. Also, the DNS forwarder needs to be
    enabled for DNS lookups by unauthenticated clients to work.</para>

    <para>Plan carefully when you will make changes to the Captive Portal
    configuration. Changing any settings on the main Captive Portal
    configuration window will disconnect all clients!</para>

    <para>Because of the way Captive Portal is implemented, it cannot be used
    on more than one interface.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Additional Information</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Is there any extra Captive Portal RADIUS functionality
      available?</title>

      <para>Jonathan De Graeve has implemented a number of new RADIUS features
      for Captive Portal that will be implemented in a future beta version.
      For now, these features are available on test images available for
      download from <ulink url="http://inf.imelda.be/downloads/m0n0wall/">
      http://inf.imelda.be/downloads/m0n0wall/</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Features currently implemented in the test images include:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>RADIUS-defined URL redirection taking precedence over URL
          redirection parameter in captive portal setup page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Multiple RADIUS server support</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Failure message on captive portal login error page, plus
          logging to the captive portal log on why authentication failed (user
          account exceeded bandwidth limit, bad password, etc.).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Cisco-compatible feature (sending calling-station-id with
          clientip and called-station-id with clientmac instead of standard
          behavior calling-station-id and clientmac).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Timeout parameter and max authentication retries
          parameter</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>retrieval of user bandwidth settings</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>retrieval of user group</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>retrieval of session-timeout</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>Retrieval means the variable is present and CAN be used, but
        there is no action bound to it yet.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Captive Portal and MAC pass-through</title>

      <para>You can utilize Captive Portal and its MAC pass-through
      functionality for rudimentary MAC address restrictions.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable Captive Portal on the desired interface (e.g. LAN) at
          the Services -&gt; Captive Portal screen. Create a HTML page of your
          liking that does not include the submit button so the user cannot
          authenticate with the captive portal. Other settings can all be left
          at their defaults.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the "Pass-through MAC" tab on the Captive Portal screen.
          Click the + to start adding permitted MAC addresses. In the MAC
          address box, type in the six hex octets separated by colons (e.g.
          ab:cd:ef:12:34:56), optionally (but recommended) enter a
          description, and click Save. Repeat for every authorized host on
          your network.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>