<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: glossary.xml,v 1.3 2005/09/07 00:45:56 chris Exp $ -->
<glossary>
  <?dbhtml filename="glossary.html"?>

  <title>Glossary</title>

  <glossdiv>
    <title></title>

    <glossentry id="gloss.ACL">
      <glossterm>ACL</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Access Control List.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.AH">
      <glossterm>AH</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Authentication Header. The Authentication Header is used to
        provide connectionless integrity and data origin authentication for IP
        datagrams. Note: AH will not work through <glossterm
        linkend="gloss.NAT">NAT</glossterm>, so if you are placing your
        m0n0wall behind another firewall or layer 2 router that is performing
        NAT AH will not work. Unless you really have a reason, use <glossterm
        linkend="gloss.ESP">ESP</glossterm>.</para>

        <glossseealso><ulink type=""
        url="http://www.networksorcery.com/enp/protocol/ah.htm">http://www.networksorcery.com/enp/protocol/ah.htm</ulink></glossseealso>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry id="gloss.BroadcastDomain">
        <glossterm>Broadcast Domain</glossterm>
        
        <glossdef>
            <para>A broadcast domain is the portion of a network sharing the same
            layer two network segment.  In a network with a single switch, the
            broadcast domain is that entire switch.  In a network with multiple switches
            interconnected by crossover cables without the use of VLAN's, the broadcast
            domain includes all of those switches.</para>
            
            <para>A single broadcast domain <emphasis>can</emphasis> contain more than
            one IP subnet, however that is generally not considered good network design.
            IP subnets should be segregated into separate broadcast domains via the use
            of separate switches, or VLAN's.  </para>
        </glossdef>
        
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>DHCP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol. A protocol to automate the
        assignment of <glossterm linkend="gloss.IP">IP</glossterm> addresses
        and related information on a network.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry id="gloss.DMZ">
        <glossterm>DMZ</glossterm>
        
        <glossdef>
            <para>A DMZ, or DeMilitarized Zone, is a segment of your network
            specifically for publicly-accessible servers.  If you are most familiar
            with residential-class routers like Linksys and similar, these
            devices generally <emphasis role="bold">incorrectly</emphasis> refer to
            inbound NAT (opening ports from the internet to your LAN) as "DMZ"
            functionality.  </para>
            
            <para>A true DMZ resides on a separate <glossterm linkend="gloss.BroadcastDomain">
            broadcast domain</glossterm> from the LAN, typically on a separate switch using a
            third interface on the firewall.  <glossterm linkend="gloss.VLAN">VLAN's</glossterm>
            can also be used, but to eliminate the potential of a switch misconfiguration exposing
            your LAN to your DMZ and the potential effects of VLAN hopping attacks, this is not
            recommended.
            </para>
            
            <para>The main purpose of a DMZ is to segregate Internet-accessible servers from
            the LAN, to protect your trusted networks if a DMZ host is compromised.</para>
            
            <formalpara>
                <title>Typical DMZ Configuration</title>
                
                <para>The following diagram illustrates a typical DMZ configuration.</para>
                
                <para>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                          <imagedata fileref="networkdiagrams/example-dmz.png" />
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </para>
                
            </formalpara>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.ESP">
      <glossterm>ESP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Encapsulating Security Payload. Encrypts and / or authenticates
        everything above the <glossterm
        linkend="gloss.IPsec">IPsec</glossterm> layer. ESP, most agree,
        renders <glossterm linkend="gloss.AH">AH</glossterm> completely
        unnecessary.</para>

        <glossseealso><ulink type=""
        url="http://www.networksorcery.com/enp/protocol/esp.htm">http://www.networksorcery.com/enp/protocol/esp.htm</ulink></glossseealso>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.FQDN">
      <glossterm>FQDN</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Fully Qualified Domain Name. The host name of a computer,
        including it's complete domain name, such as www.m0n0.ch.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.ICMP">
      <glossterm>ICMP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Internet Control Message Protocol. A protocol, layered on top of
        <glossterm linkend="gloss.IP">IP</glossterm>, used to send control
        messages between computers, such as ping.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.IP">
      <glossterm>IP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Internet Protocol. The protocol used to send packets across the
        Internet at layer three.</para>

        <glossseealso><glossterm linkend="gloss.ICMP">ICMP</glossterm>,
        <glossterm linkend="gloss.TCP">TCP</glossterm></glossseealso>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.IPsec">
      <glossterm>IPsec</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Secure transmission over <glossterm
        linkend="gloss.IP">IP</glossterm>. IPsec is an extension of the IP
        protocol used for encryption and authentication.  Encryption occurs
        at the transport layer
        of the <glossterm linkend="gloss.OSI">OSI</glossterm> model, the
        application doesn't have to support encryption for the encryption
        process to work. Therefore, all network traffic generated by
        applications can be encrypted regardless of the application</para>

        <glossseealso><ulink type=""
        url="http://www.netbsd.org/Documentation/network/ipsec/">http://www.netbsd.org/Documentation/network/ipsec/</ulink></glossseealso>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.LAN">
      <glossterm>LAN</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Local Area Network. A network that typically includes computers
        which are physically close, such as in one office, usually connected
        with hubs and switches rather than routers.</para>

        <glossseealso><glossterm linkend="gloss.VPN">VPN</glossterm>,
        <glossterm linkend="gloss.WAN">WAN</glossterm></glossseealso>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.MX">
      <glossterm>MX Records</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>MX records are DNS records that enable mail servers to find the mail servers for another domain when sending internet email.  
	When a mail server needs to send an email to example.com, it performs a DNS lookup of the MX record for the domain, and sends the email 
	to the resulting host.
        </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.NIC">
      <glossterm>NIC</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Network Interface Card.  A.k.a. network card, or Ethernet card.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.NAT">
      <glossterm>NAT</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Network Address Translation. A technique whereby <glossterm
        linkend="gloss.IP">IP</glossterm> traffic from multiple IP addresses
        behind a firewall are made to look to the outside as if they all come
        from a single IP address.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.OSI">
      <glossterm>OSI</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Systems_Interconnect">Open Systems Interconnect</ulink></para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.ProxyARP">
      <glossterm>Proxy ARP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Proxy ARP is a technique for using the ARP protocol to provide an ad hoc routing mechanism.</para>

        <para>A multi-port networking device (e.g. a router, firewall, etc.) implementing Proxy ARP will respond to
        ARP requests on one interface as being responsible for addresses of device addresses on another interface.
        The device can then receive and forward packets addressed to the other devices.  (adapted from wikipedia.org)</para>
        
        <para>In m0n0wall, Proxy ARP can be used for 1:1, advanced outbound, and server <glossterm linkend="gloss.NAT">NAT
        </glossterm>, amongst other potential uses.</para>
        
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.PPP">
      <glossterm>PPP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Point to Point Protocol.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.PPTP">
      <glossterm>PPTP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Point to Point Tunneling Protocol.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry id="gloss.racoon">
      <glossterm>Racoon</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A key management daemon.  The magic behind the
        <glossterm linkend="gloss.VPN">VPN</glossterm> power of
        m0n0wall.</para>

        <glossseealso><ulink url="http://www.kame.net/racoon/">http://www.kame.net/racoon/</ulink></glossseealso>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.TCP">
      <glossterm>TCP</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Transmission Control Protocol. A protocol, layered on top of
        <glossterm linkend="gloss.IP">IP</glossterm>, that handles connections
        and reliable delivery.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.VLAN">
      <glossterm>VLAN</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Virtual Local Area Network.  VLAN's are a common function of
        higher end switches.  They allow segregation of ports on the switch
        into separate broadcast domains.  This is generally done for security
        or performance reasons.  In very large networks, the amount of
        broadcast traffic on the wire can inhibit the performance of the
        entire network.  Segregating the network into multiple IP subnets and
        using VLAN's to separate the broadcast domain</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.VPN">
      <glossterm>VPN</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Virtual Private Network.  A connection between two or more
        machines or networks where the data travels over an insecure network
        (typically the Internet), but is encrypted to prevent eavesdropping,
        and packaged on either end in order to make the two ends appear to be
        on a <glossterm linkend="gloss.WAN">WAN</glossterm>.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="gloss.WOL">
      <glossterm>WOL - Wake on LAN</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Wake on LAN is a capability in some network cards permitting powering on the system over the network
        with a specially crafted "Magic Packet".  
        </para>
        <para>Generally a WOL cable must be attached from the <glossterm linkend="gloss.NIC">NIC</glossterm> to the
        motherboard of the system.  Most NIC's built into the motherboard have this support built in.  You must enable
        WOL in the BIOS of the machine.  This is generally off by default.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>


    <glossentry id="gloss.WAN">
      <glossterm>WAN</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Wide Area Network. A network that spans a large area, typically
        including routers, gateways, and many different <glossterm
        linkend="gloss.IP">IP</glossterm> address groups.</para>
        
        <para>In the context of firewalls, the WAN interface is the one directly
        connected to the Internet.  In the context of corporate networks, the WAN
        generally refers to the network that connects all of the organization's
        locations onto the corporate network.  Historically this was accomplished
        with expensive private leased lines like frame relay and similar technologies.
        With the low cost and widespread availability of broadband Internet connections,
        many organizations are switching to using VPN in lieu of leased lines.  VPN
        provides the same functionality, though is not as reliable as leased lines and
        has higher latency.</para>
        
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>