<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: hardware.xml,v 1.17 2005/10/07 06:03:13 chris Exp $ -->
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="hardware.html"?>

  <title>Hardware Compatibility</title>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-arch.html"?>

    <title>Supported Hardware Architectures </title>

    <para>m0n0wall is supported only on the x86 architecture.  The types of devices
    supported range from standard PC's to a variety of embedded devices.  It is
    targeted at embedded x86-based PCs.</para>
    
    <para>This <emphasis role="bold">excludes</emphasis> non-x86 devices like the
    MIPS-based Linksys devices, ARM-based D-Link devices, etc.  FreeBSD does not
    support the MIPS or ARM platforms.  For a list of FreeBSD supported platforms,
    see <ulink url="http://www.freebsd.org/platforms/index.html">this page</ulink>.
    Some shown there are not yet functional (like MIPS, for example).  The only
    platform supported by m0n0wall at this point is x86.</para>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-pc.html"?>

    <title>Supported Standard PC-Based Hardware </title>
    
    <para>m0n0wall will run on any standard x86 PC that supports at least two 
	network interfaces.</para>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Minimum Requirements</title>
    
        <para><emphasis role="bold">486 processor</emphasis> - Any 486 or
        higher processor is sufficient for m0n0wall.  Exactly how much
        processor you will need for your particular implementation varies
        depending on your Internet connection bandwidth, number of
        simultaneous connections required, what features you will use, etc.
        For most deployments, a 486 or Pentium processor is sufficient. </para>
    
        <para><emphasis role="bold">64 MB of RAM</emphasis> - 64 MB RAM is
        the official suggested minimum.  The CD version of m0n0wall has
        been reported to work fine for some people with only 32 MB.  When
        using the CompactFlash or hard drive versions of m0n0wall, expect
        upgrades to fail with less than 64 MB.  This is because m0n0wall
        stores everything in RAM and uses no swap space - when it runs out
        of RAM, it has nothing to fall back on.</para>
    
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Recommended System BIOS Changes</title>
        
        <para>There are some BIOS settings that may need to be changed for
        m0n0wall to function properly.  </para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Plug and Play OS</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>Most system BIOS have a setting for "Plug and Play OS" or something
        similar.  This should always be set to "no" or "disable".  With this setting
        turned off, the BIOS assigns system resources rather than leaving that up
        to the OS.  FreeBSD (and hence m0n0wall) works best when the BIOS handles
        this task.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Disabling Unnecessary Devices</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>You most likely won't have to worry about this, but if you have
        hardware-related issues, we recommend disabling all unnecessary devices
        in the BIOS, such as onboard sound, and in some cases parallel ports,
        serial ports, and other unused devices.  If you aren't using it, it is safe
        to disable it.  </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Storage Medium</title>
        <para>m0n0wall will run off of a CompactFlash card, hard drive, or CD with floppy to store the configuration.</para>
    
        <para><emphasis role="bold">CompactFlash</emphasis></para>
        <para>At least an 8 MB CompactFlash card is required.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hard Drive</emphasis></para>
        <para>Any IDE or SCSI (with supported controller) hard drive will work fine with m0n0wall.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">CD/floppy setup</emphasis></para>
        <para>Any IDE or SCSI (with supported controller) CD-ROM or DVD drive will work with
            m0n0wall.  Also required for this setup is a 1.44 MB floppy drive with blank floppy disk formatted with
            MS-DOS/FAT file system.  Any standard floppy drive will work.  For this setup, you must have a PC that
            supports booting from CD-ROM.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Zip drive setup</emphasis></para>
        <para>Starting with 1.2b3, m0n0wall can run the hard drive image from a
        Zip drive.  Write the disk the same way you would write a hard drive.  </para>
            
    </sect2>   
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-embedded.html"?>
    
    <title>Supported Embedded Devices</title>
    
    <para>The following embedded x86 machines will run m0n0wall.  </para>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Soekris Engineering</title>
    
        <para>All <ulink url="http://soekris.com">Soekris</ulink> devices are
        fully compatible with m0n0wall.  For the net4501 and other
        45xx models, use the net45xx image.  For the net4801 and net4826, use
        the net48xx image.  </para>
    
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Specifications</emphasis></para>
        
        <blockquote>
      <literallayout class="monospaced">
    net4501-30: 133 Mhz CPU, 64 Mbyte SDRAM, 3 Ethernet, 2 Serial, CF socket, 1 Mini-PCI socket, 3.3V PCI connector.
    net4511-30: 100 Mhz CPU, 64 Mbyte SDRAM, 2 Ethernet, 1 Serial, CF socket, 1 Mini-PCI socket, Single PC-Card socket, PoE.
    net4521-30: 133 Mhz CPU, 64 Mbyte SDRAM, 2 Ethernet, 1 Serial, CF socket, 1 Mini-PCI socket, Dual PC-Card socket, PoE.
    net4526-20: 100 Mhz CPU, 32 Mbyte SDRAM, 1 Ethernet, 1 Serial, 16 Mbyte CF Flash, 2 Mini-PCI sockets, PoE.
    net4526-30: 133 Mhz CPU, 64 Mbyte SDRAM, 1 Ethernet, 1 Serial, 64 Mbyte CF Flash, 2 Mini-PCI sockets, PoE.
    net4801-50: 266 Mhz CPU, 128 Mbyte SDRAM, 3 Ethernet, 2 serial, USB connector, CF socket, 44 pins IDE connector, 1 Mini-PCI socket, 3.3V PCI connector.
    </literallayout></blockquote>

        <para>For a detailed walk-through of getting up and running with m0n0wall
        on Soekris hardware, see the <ulink url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/quickstartsoekris/">
        m0n0wall Soekris Quick Start Guide</ulink>.  </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>PC Engines WRAP</title>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Wireless Router Application Platform (WRAP)</emphasis></para>
        
        <para><ulink url="http://www.pcengines.ch/">PC Engines</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.pcengines.ch/wrap.htm">WRAP</ulink> boards
        are fully compatible with m0n0wall.  Use the WRAP images available on the download page.  </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Nokia IPxxx boxes</title>
        
        <para>The Nokia IPxxx boxes were built to run Check Point, but they are standard PC hardware and will run m0n0wall.</para>

        <para>You can pick up a used IP110 or IP120 for around $100 USD on eBay.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">IP110, 120 and 130</emphasis></para>
        <literallayout>
            Three 10/100 Ethernet interfaces
            National GX1 300 MHz processor
            64 MB RAM on 110, 128 MB on 120, 256 MB on 130
            5 GB hard drive
            Two serial ports (auxiliary and console)
            Quiet - hard drive is only moving component, no fans
        </literallayout>
        
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">IP330</emphasis></para>
        <literallayout>
            Three 10/100 Ethernet interfaces
            National GX1 300 MHz processor
            RAM typically between 64 MB and 256 MB
            Hard drive typically ranging from 4-20 GB
            Two serial ports (auxiliary and console)
            Has case fans, so not quiet like the IP1xx
        </literallayout>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">IP440, 530, 650, 740</emphasis></para>

        <para>Even in the used market, these boxes are usually out of the price
        range for a typical m0n0wall installation, and you can buy or assemble a
        comparable standard PC for far cheaper.  But, if you have one laying
        around or can find one cheaply, these will run m0n0wall.  Some of the
        optional interfaces like HSSI, T-1 CSU/DSU, V.35 and X.21 serial, OC-3
        ATM, FDDI, etc. will not work, but the Ethernet will work fine.</para>

        <para><note>There are some tricks to getting m0n0wall working on Nokia
        hardware because the NIC's initially show MAC address ff:ff:ff:ff:ff:ff.
        For pictures and complete instructions, see
        <ulink url="http://chrisbuechler.com/m0n0wall/nokia/ip110.html">this
        page.</ulink></note></para>

    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>NexCom NexGate Appliances</title>
        
        <para><ulink url="http://nexcom.com">NexCom's</ulink> <ulink
        url="http://nsa.nexcom.com.tw/index.jsp">Nexgate</ulink>
        line of appliances all support m0n0wall.  These are much more
        high end than the WRAP and Soekris platforms, and hence are much
        more costly.  There are a number of different configurations
        available, with prices starting over $500 USD for the most
        basic model.  Contact NexCom for pricing.  </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-virtualization.html"?>
    <title>Virtualization</title>
    
    <para>m0n0wall works fine with most virtualization software like VMware
    Workstation, GSX, and ESX, and Microsoft Virtual PC and Virtual Server.
    </para>
    
    <para>While these types of configurations work, we don't recommend running
    any production firewalls under any sort of virtualization.  m0n0wall as a
    virtual machine is very well suited to testing and development environments.
    In fact much of the m0n0wall documentation is written by Chris Buechler using
    VMware Workstation teams with 10-15 virtual machines.  </para>
    
    <para>If you plan to use m0n0wall in VMware for testing purposes, we suggest
    using Chris Buechler's pre-configured <ulink
    url="http://chrisbuechler.com/index.php?id=18">m0n0wall VMware images</ulink>.
    </para>
    
    <para>For using m0n0wall in MS VPC or VS, you may want to check out the
    pre-configured <ulink url="http://chrisbuechler.com/index.php?id=31">m0n0wall
    images for Microsoft Virtual PC and Virtual Server</ulink> for download
    from Chris Buechler's site, make by Chris Nottingham.
    </para>
    
  </sect1>
        
  
  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-sizing.html"?>
    <title>Hardware Sizing</title>
    
    <para>Determining the exact hardware sizing for your m0n0wall deployment can
    be difficult at best, because network environments differ dramatically.  The
    following will provide some base guidelines on choosing what hardware is sufficient
    for your installation.  Stated throughput numbers are very conservative for most
    environments, leaving some room for error and future expandability.</para>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Embedded Devices</title>
        
        <para>The following can be used as a rough guide to determining which embedded
        platform, if any, is suitable for your environment. 
        </para>
        
        <sect3>
            <title>Soekris 45xx</title>
            
            <para>The Soekris 45xx line is sufficient for any Internet connection under
            10 Mbps.  If IPsec VPN's will be used, a 45xx is sufficient up to around 3 Mbps of
            sustained IPsec throughput.  Other features will not cause enough of a
            performance hit to make a substantial difference.  
            </para>
            
            <para>One thing to keep in mind is the maximum throughput between interfaces, if
            you plan on utilizing a DMZ segment or second LAN segment.  A 45xx maxes out at
            around 17 Mbps.  If you need more than 17 Mbps of throughput between your internal
            networks, you will need to go with a faster platform.</para>
            
        </sect3>
        
        <sect3>
            <title>Soekris 48xx</title>
            
            <para>The Soekris 48xx line is sufficient for most Internet connections less
            than 30 Mbps.  If IPsec VPN's will be used, a 48xx is sufficient up to around
            </para>
            
            <para>One thing to keep in mind is the maximum throughput between interfaces, if
            you plan on utilizing a DMZ segment or second LAN segment.  A 48xx maxes out at
            around 40 Mbps.  If you need more than 40 Mbps of throughput between your internal
            networks, you will need to go with a faster platform.</para>
            
        </sect3>
        
        <sect3>
            <title>WRAP</title>
            
            <para>WRAP boards are sufficient for most Internet connections less than 30 Mbps.
            If IPsec VPN's will be used, a WRAP is sufficient up to around
            </para>

            <para>One thing to keep in mind is the maximum throughput between interfaces, if
            you plan on utilizing a DMZ segment or second LAN segment.  A 48xx maxes out at
            around 40 Mbps.  If you need more than 40 Mbps of throughput between your internal
            networks, you will need to go with a faster platform.</para>
            
        </sect3>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Network Cards</title>
        
        <note>This is only applicable to PC-based installations</note>
        
        <para>Your selection of network cards (NIC's) is the single most important
        performance factor in your setup.  Cheap NIC's will keep your CPU very busy
        with interrupt handling, causing your CPU to be the bottleneck in your
        configuration.  A quality NIC can increase your maximum throughput as much
        as two to three fold, if not more.  </para>
        
        <para>FreeBSD refers to network cards by their driver name followed by the
        interface number.  For example, if you have two Intel Pro/100 cards (fxp
        driver) and one 3Com 3C905 card (xl driver), you will have interfaces fxp0,
        fxp1, and xl0 respectively.
        </para>
        
        <para>Intel Pro/100 and Pro/1000 cards tend to be the best performing and
        most reliable on m0n0wall.  Cheap cards like those containing Realtek
        chipsets (FreeBSD rl driver) are very poor performers in comparison.  If you
        are purchasing NIC's for your m0n0wall installation, we strongly recommend
        purchasing Intel cards.  You can find them on ebay for less than $30 USD for
        3-5 cards in a bulk lot.  </para>
        
        <para>For low throughput environments, like any typical broadband connection
        6 Mbps or less, any NIC will suffice.  If you require fast throughput (more than
        30-40 Mbps) between interfaces for multiple LAN networks, or between a DMZ and
        your LAN, then using quality NIC's becomes much more important.</para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Processor</title>
        
        <para>Your CPU will generally be the bottleneck in your system.  Network throughput
        with cheap NIC's will max out your CPU long before it will get maxed out with quality
        NIC's, so the most important factor with CPU sizing is the quality of your NIC's.</para>
        
        <para>If you are using good quality NIC's like Intel cards, as a general measure, a Pentium
        will suffice up to 30-40 Mbps, a Pentium III will do 100 Mb at wire speed, and for gigabit
        wire speeds you will need a 2.8+ GHz Pentium 4.  </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>RAM</title>
        
        <para>The stock m0n0wall images will not use more than 64 MB RAM under any circumstance.
        You can install as much memory as you like, but even with all features enabled and heavy
        loads, you will not exhaust 64 MB. </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Storage Medium</title>
        
        <para>m0n0wall will work fine on any hard drive or compact flash card at least 8 MB in
        size.  At boot, m0n0wall is loaded into RAM and runs from RAM, so the speed and type
        of storage medium used is not a factor in system performance.  </para>
        
        <para>Slower storage mediums like compact flash will take slightly longer to boot than
        hard drives will, but boot time is the only performance factor in selecting your storage
        medium.  Compact flash is suggested for maximum reliability since it is much less likely
        to fail than a hard drive.</para>  
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>High Throughput Environments</title>
        
        <para>In environments where extremely high throughput through several interfaces is
        required, especially with gigabit interfaces, PCI bus speed must be taken into account.
        When using multiple interfaces in the same system, the bandwidth of the PCI bus
        can easily become a bottleneck.  Most typical motherboards only have one or two PCI
        buses, and each can run an absolute maximum of 133 MBps, or 1064 Mbps.  That's less
        than one gigabit interface can transfer.  PCI-X can transfer up to 1056 MBps, or about
        8.25 Gbps.</para>
        
        <para>If you need sustained gigabit throughput at wire speed, you will want a
        server-class motherboard with PCI-X slots and PCI-X NIC's.</para>
        
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
        
  
  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-wireless.html"?>
    <title>Wireless Cards</title>
    
    <para>Before considering using m0n0wall as an access point, read
    <link linkend="FAQ.AP">this FAQ entry</link>.</para>

    <para>These cards are broken into two lists - readily available cards, and
        discontinued / difficult to obtain cards.  </para>    
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Unsupported Cards</title>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Currently all g, b/g, and a/b/g wireless cards are incompatible
        with m0n0wall.</emphasis>  These require drivers that are only found in FreeBSD 5.x and 6.x,
        while m0n0wall is on 4.11.  They will be supported when m0n0wall is <link linkend="FAQ.FBSD5">
        on a newer version of FreeBSD</link>.</para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Readily Available Cards</title>
        
        <para>The following list, to the best of our knowledge, is 100% accurate.  Please report any findings
        to the contrary to <ulink url="mailto:cbuechler@gmail.com">Chris Buechler</ulink>.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Not all wireless cards support hostap mode!</emphasis> (i.e. can function
        as an access point)  This is a limitation of the hardware itself, not m0n0wall or FreeBSD.  If this list does not
        say "no hostap" next to the card, it <emphasis>should</emphasis> support hostap.</para>
        
        <para><note>The m0n0wall Documentation Project does not endorse any
                vendors you may find through froogle.google.com.  We simply link
                there for your convenience.  The searches provided may also
                bring up unrelated hardware in addition to the compatible
                hardware.</note></para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=3crwe737a">3COM 3crwe737A AirConnect Wireless LAN PC Card</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=cisco+340">Cisco Systems Aironet 340</ulink> - <emphasis role="bold">no hostap</emphasis></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=cisco+350">Cisco Systems Aironet 350</ulink> - <emphasis role="bold">no hostap</emphasis></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=compaq+wl100">Compaq WL100</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=compaq+wl110">Compaq WL110</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=dwl-520">D-Link DWL-520</ulink> - <emphasis role="bold">NOT DWL-520+</emphasis> as it uses a different, unsupported, chipset.</listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=dwl-650">D-Link DWL-650</ulink> - Revisions A1-J3 ONLY.  K1, L1, M, and P revisions not supported.</listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=TrueMobile+1150">Dell TrueMobile 1150 Series</ulink> - <emphasis role="bold">no hostap</emphasis></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=Intel+PRO%2FWireless+2011">Intel PRO/Wireless 2011 LAN PC Card</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=wpc11">Linksys Instant Wireless WPC11</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=Netgear+MA311">Netgear MA311</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=Netgear+MA401">Netgear MA401</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=SMC+2632W">SMC 2632W PC Card</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=SMC+2602W">SMC 2602W PCI</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=US+Robotics+Wireless+Card+2410">US Robotics Wireless Card 2410</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://netgate.com/EL2511.html">NL-2511CD</ulink></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">miniPCI</emphasis></para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://tinyurl.com/65ye7">2511MP</ulink></listitem>
            <listitem><ulink url="http://froogle.google.com/froogle?q=TrueMobile+1150">Dell TrueMobile 1150 Series</ulink></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Discontinued / Difficult to Obtain</title>

        <note>Some of the following do not support hostap.  To determine if they do, search Google for the card
        name and FreeBSD, to determine which driver the card uses.  If it is 'wi', it will work.  Cards that use
        drivers other than wi do not support hostap.</note>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Accton airDirect WN3301</listitem>
            <listitem>Addtron AWA100</listitem>
            <listitem>Adtec ADLINK340APC</listitem>
            <listitem>Aironet 4500/4800 series (PCMCIA, PCI, and ISA adapters are all supported)</listitem>
            <listitem>Airway 802.11 Adapter</listitem>
            <listitem>Avaya Wireless PC Card</listitem>
            <listitem>BayStack 650 and 660</listitem>
            <listitem>Blue Concentric Circle CF Wireless LAN Model WL-379F</listitem>
            <listitem>BreezeNET PC-DS.11</listitem>
            <listitem>Buffalo WLI-CF-S11G</listitem>
            <listitem>Cabletron RoamAbout 802.11 DS</listitem>
            <listitem>Corega KK Wireless LAN PCC-11, PCCA-11, PCCB-11</listitem>
            <listitem>ELECOM Air@Hawk/LD-WL11/PCC</listitem>
            <listitem>ELSA AirLancer MC-11</listitem>
            <listitem>Farallon Skyline 11Mbps Wireless</listitem>
            <listitem>Farallon SkyLINE Wireless</listitem>
            <listitem>ICOM SL-1100</listitem>
            <listitem>Icom SL-200</listitem>
            <listitem>IBM High Rate Wireless LAN PC Card</listitem>
            <listitem>IO Data WN-B11/PCM</listitem>
            <listitem>Laneed Wireless card</listitem>
            <listitem>Lucent Technologies WaveLAN/IEEE 802.11 PCMCIA and ISA standard speed (2Mbps) and turbo speed (6Mbps) wireless network adapters and workalikes</listitem>
            <listitem>Lucent WaveLAN/IEEE 802.11</listitem>
            <listitem>Melco Airconnect WLI-PCM-S11, WLI-PCM-L11</listitem>
            <listitem>Melco WLI-PCM</listitem>
            <listitem>NCR WaveLAN/IEEE 802.11</listitem>
            <listitem>NEC Wireless Card CMZ-RT-WP</listitem>
            <listitem>NEC Aterm WL11C (PC-WL/11C)</listitem>
            <listitem>NEC PK-WL001</listitem>
            <listitem>NEL SSMagic</listitem>
            <listitem>Netwave AirSurfer Plus and AirSurfer Pro</listitem>
            <listitem>PLANEX GeoWave/GW-NS110</listitem>
            <listitem>Proxim Harmony, RangeLAN-DS</listitem>
            <listitem>Raytheon Raylink PC Card</listitem>
            <listitem>Sony PCWA-C100</listitem>
            <listitem>TDK LAK-CD011WL</listitem>
            <listitem>Toshiba Wireless LAN Card</listitem>
            <listitem>Webgear Aviator</listitem>
            <listitem>Webgear Aviator Pro</listitem>
            <listitem>Xircom Wireless Ethernet adapter (rebadged Aironet)</listitem>
            <listitem>ZoomAir 4000</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    

  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="hardware-ethernet.html"?>
    <title>Ethernet Cards</title>
    
    <para>m0n0wall supports most any Ethernet card (NIC).  However some are more reliable,
    less troublesome, and faster than others.  In general, you'll find the opinion
    of the m0n0wall community to be that cheap chipsets, such as Realtek
    chipsets, are more troublesome and slower than quality NIC's like Intel
    no matter what software and OS you are running.  It is especially important to run quality
    NIC's if you are running a high traffic firewall.  The cheaper ones will flood your
    system with interrupts when under load.  Because interrupts can take up
    substantial amounts of CPU time
    and the first system bottleneck on a firewall is typically CPU, 
    good quality NIC's are extremely important in higher throughput 
    environments.
    </para>
    
    <para>I would personally recommend Intel NIC's over any others.  The
    Intel PRO/100 cards are easy to find, and if you have to buy
    some, they're cheap.  You could outfit your firewall with
    three interfaces for less than $25 USD on eBay. </para>

    <sect2>
	<title>Supported Cards</title>

	<para>We recommend just trying whatever Ethernet cards you 
	already have without bothering with the compatibility list 
	since it includes virtually every NIC.  One notable exception
	is some newer gigabit cards.  For this reason, we suggest 
	checking the list below for gigabit cards, or just get Intel
	Pro/1000 cards which are well supported.  </para>

	<para>If you have any question on what cards are compatible, 
	refer to the <ulink url="http://www.freebsd.org/releases/4.11R/hardware-i386.html#ETHERNET">
	FreeBSD 4.11-RELEASE Hardware Notes</ulink> for a 
	list of supported Ethernet cards.  </para>

    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>ISA Network Cards</title>
        
        <para>While a large number of ISA Ethernet cards are supported, we recommend
        you stay away from them if possible.  They can be very time consuming
        and difficult to get working properly.  The cost of a few PCI network cards
        is, in my opinion, well worth the headaches it will prevent.  The only time
        you should use ISA NIC's is when you don't have any or enough PCI slots.  
        </para>
        
        <para>If you have ISA cards that you'd like to try, by all means give them
        a shot.  It might work out of the box, especially if you only have one ISA
        card along with some PCI cards.  But if you experience problems
        getting them to work, you've been warned! </para>
        
        <para>If you need to get an ISA card working, you'll probably need to change
        some things.  First, most ISA NIC's, including the common 3Com ISA cards,
        have a "plug and play" mode on the card that is selected by default.  FreeBSD
        doesn't always play nicely with devices that are set to plug and play.  In the
        case of the 3Com cards, 3Com has a DOS utility on their support site that you
        will have to run in DOS to set up the resources on all of the cards manually.
        Check your network card manufacturer's support site for information on
        disabling any plug and play settings on ISA cards.  This is typically jumpers on
        the card or a firmware utility.</para>
        
        <para>Another thing you may have to do is to change some settings in the
        system BIOS.  For example you may need to set the IRQ used by the NIC to
        ISA/PnP.</para>
        
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
