<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: intro.xml,v 1.4 2005/10/04 02:53:27 chris Exp $ -->
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="intro.html"?>

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-is.html"?>

    <title>What m0n0wall is</title>

    <para>m0n0wall is a complete embedded firewall software package that, when
    used together with an embedded PC, provides all the important features of
    commercial firewall boxes (including ease of use) at a fraction of the
    price (free software). m0n0wall is based on a bare-bones version of
    FreeBSD, along with a web server (thttpd), PHP and a few other utilities.
    The entire system configuration is stored in one single XML text file to
    keep things transparent.</para>

    <para>m0n0wall is probably the first UNIX system that has its boot-time
    configuration done with PHP, rather than the usual shell scripts, and that
    has the entire system configuration stored in XML format.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-not.html"?>

    <title>What m0n0wall is not</title>

    <para>m0n0wall is a firewall, and the purpose of a firewall is to provide
    security. The more functionality is added, the greater the chance that a
    vulnerability in that additional functionality will compromise the
    security of the firewall.  It is the opinion of the m0n0wall founder and core
    contributors that anything outside the base services of a layer 3 and 4 firewall
    do not belong in m0n0wall.  Some services that may be appropriate are very CPU-intensive and
    memory hungry, and m0n0wall is focused towards embedded devices with limited CPU and
    memory resources.  The non-persistant filesystem due to our focus on Compact Flash
    installations is another limiting factor.  Lastly, image size constraints eliminate
    other possibilities.</para>
    
    <para>We feel these services should be run on another server, and are intentionally not part of m0n0wall:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Intrusion Detection/Prevention System</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Proxy Server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Packet inspection at any layers other than 3 and 4</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A general purpose web server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An FTP server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A network time server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A log file analyzer</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For the same reason, m0n0wall does not allow logins: there is no
    login prompt at the console (it displays a <link
    linkend="Config.Console">menu</link> instead), and no telnet or ssh
    daemon.</para>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-history.html"?>

    <title>History</title>

    <para>Manuel Kasper, m0n0wall's author, says:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Ever since I started playing with packet filters on embedded PCs,
      I wanted to have a nice web-based GUI to control all aspects of my
      firewall without having to type a single shell command. There are
      numerous efforts to create nice firewall packages with web interfaces on
      the Internet (most of them Linux based), but none met all my
      requirements (free, fast, simple, clean and with all the features I
      need). So, I eventually started writing my own web GUI. But soon I
      figured that I didn't want to create another incarnation of webmin ? I
      wanted to create a complete, new embedded firewall software package. It
      all evolved to the point where one could plug in the box, set the LAN IP
      address via the serial console, log into the web interface and set it
      up. Then I decided that I didn't like the usual bootup system
      configuration with shell scripts (I already had to write a C program to
      generate the filter rules since that's almost impossible in a shell
      script), and since my web interface was based on PHP, it didn't take me
      long to figure out that I might use PHP for the system configuration as
      well. That way, the configuration data would no longer have to be stored
      in text files that can be parsed in a shell script ? It could now be
      stored in an XML file. So I completely rewrote the whole system again,
      not changing much in the look-and-feel, but quite a lot "under the
      hood".</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The first public beta release of m0n0wall was on February 15, 2003.
    Version 1.0 was released exactly one year later, on February 15, 2004.  
    Between those two were an additional 26 public beta releases, an average
    of one release every two weeks.  Version 1.1 was released in August 2004, 
    with 1.11 released with a security update for m0n0wall's dynamic DNS 
    component ez-ipupdate on November 11, 2004.  Version 1.2 has been in beta 
    since, with a final release in October 2005.  A complete list of changes for each
    version can be found on the m0n0wall web site under <ulink
    url="http://www.m0n0.ch/wall/changelog.php">Change Log</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-features.html"?>

    <title>Features</title>

    <para>m0n0wall provides many of the features of expensive commercial
    firewalls, and some you won't find in any commercial firewalls, including:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>web interface (supports SSL)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>serial console interface for recovery</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>set LAN IP address</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>reset password</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>restore factory defaults</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>reboot system</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>wireless support (access point with PRISM-II/2.5 cards, BSS/IBSS
        with other cards including Cisco)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>stateful packet filtering</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>block/pass rules</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>logging</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT/PAT (including 1:1)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DHCP client, PPPoE and PPTP support on the WAN interface</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IPsec VPN tunnels (IKE; with support for hardware crypto cards
        and mobile clients)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PPTP VPN (with RADIUS server support)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>static routes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DHCP server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>caching DNS forwarder</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DynDNS client</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SNMP agent</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>traffic shaper</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>firmware upgrade through the web browser</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>configuration backup/restore</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>host/network aliases</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2>
      <title>Components</title>

      <para>m0n0wall contains the following software components:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>FreeBSD components (kernel, user programs)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>ipfilter</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>PHP (CGI version)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>thttpd</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>MPD</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>ISC DHCP server</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>ez-ipupdate (for DynDNS updates)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Dnsmasq (for the caching DNS forwarder)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>racoon (for IPsec IKE)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Specifications</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The m0n0wall system currently takes up <emphasis
          role="bold">less than 5 MB</emphasis> on a Compact Flash card or
          CD-ROM.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On a net4501, m0n0wall provides a WAN &lt;-&gt; LAN TCP
          throughput of about <emphasis role="bold">17 Mbps</emphasis>,
          including NAT, when run with the default configuration. On faster
          platforms (like net4801 or WRAP), throughput in excess of 50 Mbps is
          possible (and up to gigabit speeds with newer standard PCs).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On a net4501, m0n0wall boots to a fully working state in less
          than <emphasis role="bold">40 seconds</emphasis> after power-up,
          including POST (with a properly configured BIOS).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-license.html"?>

    <title>Software Copyright and Distribution (Licenses)</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">m0n0wall is Copyright © 2002-2004 by Manuel
    Kasper. All rights reserved.</emphasis></para>

    <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
    modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
    met:</para>

    <para>1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</para>

    <para>2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
    documentation and/or other materials provided with the
    distribution.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS'' AND ANY
    EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED
    WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
    DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT,
    INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
    (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
    SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
    CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT
    LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY
    OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
    SUCH DAMAGE.</emphasis></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Other Software Packages</title>

      <para>m0n0wall is based upon/includes various free software packages,
      listed below. The author of m0n0wall would like to thank the authors of
      these software packages for their efforts.</para>

      <para>FreeBSD (http://www.freebsd.org) Copyright © 1994-2003 FreeBSD,
      Inc. All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>This product includes PHP, freely available from
      http://www.php.net. Copyright © 1999 - 2003 The PHP Group. All rights
      reserved.</para>

      <para>mini_httpd (http://www.acme.com/software/mini_httpd) Copyright ©
      1999, 2000 by Jef Poskanzer &lt;jef@acme.com&gt;. All rights
      reserved.</para>

      <para>ISC DHCP server (http://www.isc.org/products/DHCP) Copyright ©
      1996-2003 Internet Software Consortium. All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>ipfilter (http://www.ipfilter.org) Copyright © 1993-2002 by Darren
      Reed.</para>

      <para>MPD - Multi-link PPP daemon for FreeBSD
      (http://www.dellroad.org/mpd) Copyright © 1995-1999 Whistle
      Communications, Inc. All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>ez-ipupdate (http://www.gusnet.cx/proj/ez-ipupdate) Copyright ©
      1998-2001 Angus Mackay. All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>Circular log support for FreeBSD syslogd
      (http://software.wwwi.com/syslogd) Copyright © 2001 Jeff Wheelhouse
      (jdw@wwwi.com)</para>

      <para>Dnsmasq - a DNS forwarder for NAT firewalls
      (http://www.thekelleys.org.uk) Copyright © 2000-2003 Simon Kelley</para>

      <para>Racoon (http://www.kame.net/racoon) Copyright © 1995-2002 WIDE
      Project. All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>before version pb23: watchdogd (watchdog) Copyright © 2002-2003
      Dirk-Willem van Gulik. All rights reserved. This product includes
      software developed by the Stichting Wireless Leiden
      (http://www.wirelessleiden.nl). See LICENSE for more licensing
      information.</para>

      <para>msntp (http://www.hpcf.cam.ac.uk/export) Copyright © 1996, 1997,
      2000 N.M. Maclaren, University of Cambridge. All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>UCD-SNMP (http://www.ece.ucdavis.edu/ucd-snmp) Copyright © 1989,
      1991, 1992 by Carnegie Mellon University. Copyright © 1996, 1998-2000
      The Regents of the University of California. All rights reserved.
      Copyright © 2001-2002, Network Associates Technology, Inc. All rights
      reserved. Portions of this code are copyright © 2001-2002, Cambridge
      Broadband Ltd. All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>choparp (http://choparp.sourceforge.net) Copyright © 1997
      Takamichi Tateoka (tree@mma.club.uec.ac.jp) Copyright © 2002 Thomas
      Quinot (thomas@cuivre.fr.eu.org)</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Intro.Credits">
    <?dbhtml filename="intro-credits.html"?>

    <title id="Intro.Credits.title">Contributors and Credits</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Code</title>

      <para>m0n0wall was written by Manuel Kasper.</para>

      <para>The following persons have contributed code to m0n0wall:</para>

      <para>Bob Zoller (bob at kludgebox dot com): Diagnostics: Ping function;
      WLAN channel auto-select; DNS forwarder</para>

      <para>Michael Mee (m0n0wall at mikemee dot com): Timezone and NTP client
      support</para>

      <para>Magne Andreassen (magne dot andreassen at bluezone dot no): Remote
      syslog'ing; some code bits for DHCP server on optional interfaces</para>

      <para>Rob Whyte (rob at g-labs dot com): Idea/code bits for encrypted
      webGUI passwords; minimalized SNMP agent</para>

      <para>Petr Verner (verner at ipps dot cz): Advanced outbound NAT:
      destination selection</para>

      <para>Bruce A. Mah (bmah at acm dot org): Filtering bridge
      patches</para>

      <para>Jim McBeath (monowall at j dot jimmc dot org): Filter rule patches
      (ordering, block/pass, disabled); better status page; webGUI assign
      network ports page</para>

      <para>Chris Olive (chris at technologEase dot com): enhanced "execute
      command" page</para>

      <para>Pauline Middelink (middelink at polyware dot nl): DHCP client:
      send hostname patch</para>

      <para>Björn Pålsson (bjorn at networksab dot com): DHCP lease list
      page</para>

      <para>Peter Allgeyer (allgeyer at web dot de): "reject" type filter
      rules</para>
      
      <para>Thierry Lechat (dev at lechat dot org): SVG-based traffic grapher</para>

      <para>Steven Honson (steven at honson dot org): per-user IP address assignments for PPTP VPN</para>

      <para>Kurt Inge Smådal (kurt at emsp dot no): NAT on optional interfaces</para>

      <para>Dinesh Nair (dinesh at alphaque dot com): captive portal: pass-through MAC/IP addresses, RADIUS authentication
      HTTP server concurrency limit</para>

      <para>Justin Ellison (justin at techadvise dot com): traffic shaper TOS matching; magic shaper; DHCP deny unknown clients;
      IPsec user FQDNs</para>

      <para>Fred Wright (fw at well dot com): ipfilter window scaling fix; ipnat ICMP checksum adjustment fix </para>
      
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Documentation</title>

      <para>m0n0wall was written by Manuel Kasper.</para>

      <para>The following persons have contributed documentation to
      m0n0wall:</para>

      <para>Chris Buechler (m0n0wall at chrisbuechler.com):  Editor, numerous contributions throughout.</para>

      <para>Jim McBeath (monowall at j dot jimmc dot org): Users Guide
      outline, editing</para>

      <para>Rudi van Drunen (r.van.drunen at xs4all dot nl) with thanks to
      Manuel Kasper, Edwin Kremer, PicoBSD, Matt Simerson and John Voight:
      m0n0wall Hackers Guide, used as the basis for the old Development
      chapter, now part of the <ulink url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/dev/">m0n0wall
      Developers' Handbook</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Francisco Artes (falcor at netassassin.com): <link
      linkend="IPsec">IPsec</link> and <link linkend="PPTP">PPTP</link>
      chapters.</para>

      <para>Fred Wright (fw at well dot com):  Suggestions and review.</para>
      
      <para>Axel Eble (axel+m0n0-0001 at balrog dot de): Help with the wiki, ddclient howto contribution.</para>
      
      <para>Brian Zushi (brian at ricerage dot org): Linux CD burning instructions, documentation review and suggestions.</para>

      <para>Dino Bijedic (dino.bijedic at eracom-tech dot com): Sonicwall example VPN contribution.</para>
      
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
