<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="nat.html"?>

  <title>Network Address Translation</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>NAT Primer</title>

    <para>Network Address Translation (NAT) allows you to use RFC 1918 private
    IP addresses for addressing on your internal network, and allow all hosts
    on the internal networks to access the Internet using one public IP
    address.</para>

    <para>Due to the typical expense of obtaining public IP addresses, most
    networks do not purchase one public IP address for each network host. NAT
    allows multiple machines to connect to the Internet using a single public
    IP address. Additionally, using NAT for Internet access protects internal
    network computers from unwanted access attempts.</para>

    <para>Practically, this means that NAT allows you to receive one IP
    address from your Internet Service Provider and that everyone on your
    local network can use that IP address to access the Internet. It also
    allows you to select one or more software services (web server, file
    server, database server) to make accessible from the Internet but to limit
    access to other services or IP port numbers.</para>

    <para>m0n0wall offers 4 types of NAT:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Inbound NAT</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Outbound NAT</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Server NAT</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>1:1 NAT</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <caution>
      <para>Although a NAT rule can redirect traffic into your network you
      still must enabled filtering rules to allow the traffic to pass through
      the stateful packet firewall.</para>
    </caution>

    <sect2>
      <title>Types of NAT</title>

      <para>There are two most commonly used and most familiar types of NAT,
      bidirectional or 1:1 (pronounced one to one), and Port Address
      Translation, or PAT. In both cases m0n0wall will change the IP header of
      packets that traverse the NAT enabled interface but NAT and PAT each
      change a different part of the IP header.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>NAT Explained</title>

        <para>NAT translate the IP address in the IP packer header. NAT rules
        can be applied to TCP or UDP packets that are either incoming and/ or
        outgoing on any m0n0wall Ethernet interfaces except the LAN interface.
        Some common NAT uses include:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>sharing an Internet connection with multiple
            computers</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>adding multiple IP addresses to a WAN interface</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>translating entire IP subnets to another</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>redirect outgoing network traffic to a different IP
            address</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>redirect incoming network traffic to a different IP address
            or port address</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>spoof the IP origin of outgoing traffic to appear as coming
            from a different IP address</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>For each NAT rule, m0n0wall builds and maintains a table of
        network connections that are using each rule.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>PAT Explained</title>

        <para>PAT translates port numbers in the IP packet header. For example
        you can translate port traffic arriving on the WAN at TCP port 8080 to
        instead be redirected to port 80. When PAT is combined with NAT you
        can provide access to multiple webservers such as to send incoming
        Internet traffic for port 8001 to an internal webserver at 10.0.0.1
        port 80 and port 8002 to another web server at 10.0.0.2 port
        80.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Since only TCP and UDP packets are using port numbers, only
          these packets can benefit from PAT based translation rules.</para>
        </note>

        <para>PAT configuration is included in the NAT configuration pages
        whenever you choose to use port addresses or port ranges. Other uses
        for PAT include:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>hiding common ports to make them less obvious for script
            based attacks</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>making data appear to originate from a particular port
            address</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>allow multiple instances of a server on the same
            computer</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Proxy ARP</title>

        <para>Normally, an Ethernet interface which has an IP address being
        requested on a network will respond first to an ARP request to say
        that the IP address exists and that the Ethernet interface is
        accepting traffic for it.</para>

        <para>Without Proxy ARP you can still assign multiple IP addresses to
        the WAN interface but your Internet Service Provider must edit their
        routing tables to redirect the traffic accordingly.</para>

        <note>
          <para>PPPoE connections do not use ARP requests. If you are
          assigning multiple IP addresses to y PPPoE WAN interface then the
          service provider must route the traffic correctly.</para>
        </note>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Other Resources</title>

      <para><ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1918.html">RFC 1918 -
      Address Allocation for Private Internets</ulink> - February 1996</para>

      <para><ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1631.html">RFC 1631 - The
      IP Network Address Translator (NAT)</ulink> - May 1994</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Address_Translation"> Network
      Address Translation at Wikipedia</ulink></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="nat-inbound.html"?>

    <title>Inbound NAT</title>

    <para>Inbound NAT allows you to open up TCP and/or UDP ports or port
    ranges to hosts on networks protected by m0n0wall. You may need to open
    ports to allow certain NAT-unfriendly applications and protocols to
    function properly. Also if you run any services or applications that
    require inbound connections to a machine on your internal network, you
    will need inbound NAT.</para>

    <para>Inbound traffic is incoming data that arrivs on the selected
    m0n0wall NAT interface that has not already travelled througn th m0n0wall
    itself. For example, inbound traffic on the WAN interface coming directly
    from the Internet can have inbound rules applied to it but traffic from
    the LAN network that goes through the WAN interface cannot have inbound
    rules applied because that traffic had to pass through the m0n0wall to
    arrive at the WAN interface.</para>

    <caution>
      <para>It is not possible to access NATed services using the WAN IP
      address from within LAN (or an optional network). Only external traffic
      incoming on the selected interface will have Inbound NAT rules applied
      to it.</para>
    </caution>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="nat-outbound.html"?>

    <title>Outbound NAT</title>

    <para>By default, m0n0wall automatically adds NAT rules to all interfaces
    to NAT your internal hosts to your WAN IP address for outbound traffic.
    The only exception is for any hosts for which you have configured 1:1 NAT
    entries. Therefore, if you are using public IP addresses on any of the
    interfaces behind your m0n0wall (with the exception of bridged interfaces)
    you need to change m0n0wall's default NAT behavior by enabling advanced
    outbound NAT.</para>

    <para>If you are using public IP addresses on all the interfaces behind
    your m0n0wall, check the "Enable advanced outbound NAT" box and click
    Save. Now nothing will be NAT'ed by m0n0wall.</para>

    <para>If you have a public IP subnet off one of your interfaces behind
    m0n0wall and a private IP subnet behind another interface, you will need
    to enter your own NAT mappings on this screen. For example, if you have a
    LAN subnet of 192.168.1.0/24 and a DMZ subnet with public IP addresses,
    you will need to enable advanced outbound NAT, and click the plus at the
    bottom of this tab to add a NAT mapping for your LAN network. For this
    scenario, you will want to add a rule for interface WAN, source
    192.168.1.0/24, destination any, target box blank, and enter a description
    of your choosing.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If advanced outbound NAT is enabled in firmware 1.3 or higher, no
      outbound NAT rules will be automatically generated anymore. Instead,
      only the mappings you specify below will be used. With advanced outbound
      NAT disabled, a mapping is automatically created for each interface's
      subnet (except WAN) and any mappings specified below will be ignored. If
      you use target addresses other than the WAN interface's IP address, then
      depending on the way your WAN connection is setup, you may also need
      proxy ARP.</para>
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="nat-server.html"?>

    <title>Server NAT</title>

    <para>Server NAT gives you the ability to define extra IP addresses, other
    than the WAN IP, to be available for Inbound NAT rules. This can be used
    to allow two or more IP addresses to be accessible from the selected
    network interface.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Depending on the way your WAN connection is setup, you may also
      need proxy ARP.</para>
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="nat-1to1.html"?>

    <title>1:1 NAT</title>

    <para>1:1 NAT maps one public IP address to one private IP address by
    specifying a /32 subnet. This means having an otherwise local network
    computer accessible from the Internet through the WAN interface of your
    m0n0wall device. From a security perspective this also means that all
    traffic arriving at the WAN interface is forwarded into your network to
    the designated internal server. Be sure that you have secured the internal
    server.</para>

    <para>Additionally entire subnets can be passed through the NAT. This
    could be used for situations when multiple connected networks are using
    the same subnet, such as two sites using a 10.0.0.0/8 subnet.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Depending on the way your WAN connection is setup, you may also
      need proxy ARP.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Forwarding traffic for additional IP adresses (also known as Virtual
    IP addresses) that are not the IP address of the WAN interface is possible
    by first listing these IP addresses in the Server NAT window. Then 1:1 NAT
    is used to redirect traffic for these IP addresses to internal servers.
    For example you may have 3 IP addresses registered with the Internet
    Service Provider but only one of these can be assigned to the WAN
    interface. Using Server NAT and 1:1 NAT you can assign the additional 2 IP
    addresses to the WAN interface as well and redirect their traffic to
    specific servers.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="nat-choosing.html"?>

    <title>Choosing the appropriate NAT for your network</title>

    <para>So by now you may be thinking "so what kind of NAT do I need?", to
    which the answer is "it depends."</para>

    <para>If you do not make any of your internal servers available to the
    Internet then you do not need anything more than the default Outgoing NAT.
    This allows all of the computers on your network to share the single IP
    address that is assigned by your Internet Service Provider.</para>

    <para>If you will be publishing on or more internal servers on the
    Internet and only have <emphasis role="bold">one public IP</emphasis>, the
    only option is Inbound NAT, since that public IP will be assigned to
    m0n0wall's WAN interface.</para>

    <para>For networks with <emphasis role="bold">multiple public IP
    addresses</emphasis>, the best choice is either 1:1 NAT, or Server and
    Inbound NAT, or a combination of both. If you have more servers than
    public IP addresses, you will need to use Server and Inbound NAT, or 1:1
    NAT combined with Server and Inbound NAT. If you have sufficient public IP
    addresses for all of your servers, you should use 1:1 NAT for them
    all.</para>

    <para>Inbound and Server NAT is most suitable when you have more servers
    than public IP addresses. For example, if you have three servers, one
    HTTP, one SMTP, and one FTP, and have only two public IP addresses, you
    must use Server and Inbound NAT. For small deployments, this isn't bad to
    deal with. As the number of hosts increases, things get far more
    complicated. You'll end up having to remember things like for public IP
    address 1.2.3.4, port 80 goes to server A, port 25 goes to server B, port
    21 goes to server C, etc.</para>

    <para>If you are using software applications that open many rrandom ports
    to the Internet, such as certain video/voice IP software, you might need
    to use 1:1 NAT to be sure that whatever port is needed can get through to
    your computer.</para>

    <para>If you can't clearly picture a network in your head while
    troubleshooting problems, things become much more difficult. With ports
    going all over the place like this, once you get a number of ports
    forwarded it's extremely difficult to picture the network in your head.
    Given the complexity introduced by such a configuration, we recommend
    having one public IP address per publicly-accessible host.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>