<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="nat.html"?>

  <title>Network Address Translation</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>NAT Primer</title>
        
        <para>Network Address Translation (NAT) allows you to use RFC 1918 private IP
        addresses for addressing on your internal network, and allow all hosts on the
        internal networks to access the Internet using one public IP address.  
        </para>
        
        <para>Due to the typical expense of obtaining public IP addresses, most networks do not
        purchase one public IP address for each network host.  NAT allows multiple
        machines to connect to the Internet using a single public IP address.  </para>
        
        
        <sect2>
          <title>Types of NAT</title>
        
          <para>There are two most commonly used and most familiar
          types of NAT, bidirectional or 1:1 (pronounced one to one),
          and Port Address Translation, or PAT.  </para>
          
          <sect3>
            <title>1:1 NAT Explained</title>
            
            <para>1:1 NAT maps one public IP address to one private
            IP address, for both incoming traffic and outgoing traffic.  
            </para>
            
          </sect3>
          
          <sect3>
            <title>PAT Explained</title>
            
            <para>
            </para>
            
          </sect3>
        
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
          <title>Other Resources</title>
        
          <para><ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1918.html">RFC 1918 - Address
          Allocation for Private Internets</ulink> - February 1996</para>
        
          <para><ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1631.html">RFC 1631 - The IP
          Network Address Translator (NAT)</ulink> - May 1994</para>
        
          <para><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Address_Translation">
          Network Address Translation at Wikipedia</ulink></para>
          
        </sect2>
          
        
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="nat-inbound.html"?>
        <title>Inbound NAT</title>
        
        <para>Inbound NAT allows you to open up TCP and/or UDP ports or port ranges to
        hosts on networks protected by m0n0wall.  You may need to open ports to allow
        certain NAT-unfriendly applications and protocols to function properly.  Also if
        you run any services or applications that require inbound connections to a
        machine on your internal network, you will need inbound NAT.
        </para>
        
        
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="nat-server.html"?>
        <title>Server NAT</title>
        
        <para>Server NAT just gives you the ability to define extra IP addresses, other than
        the WAN IP, to be available for use for Inbound NAT.</para>
        
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="nat-1to1.html"?>
        <title>1:1 NAT</title>
        
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="nat-outbound.html"?>
        <title>Outbound NAT</title>
        
        <para>By default, m0n0wall automatically adds NAT rules to all interfaces
        to NAT your internal hosts to your WAN IP address for outbound traffic.
        The only exception is for any hosts for which you have configured 1:1 NAT
        entries.  Therefore, if you are using public IP addresses on any of the
        interfaces behind your m0n0wall (with the exception of bridged interfaces)
        you need to change m0n0wall's default NAT behavior by enabling advanced
        outbound NAT.
        </para>
        
        <para>If you are using public IP addresses on all the interfaces behind
        your m0n0wall, check the "Enable advanced outbound NAT" box and click Save.
        Now nothing will be NAT'ed by m0n0wall.  </para>
        
        <para>If you have a public IP subnet off one of your interfaces behind m0n0wall
        and a private IP subnet behind another interface, you will need to enter your
        own NAT mappings on this screen.  For example, if you have a LAN subnet of
        192.168.1.0/24 and a DMZ subnet with public IP addresses, you will need to
        enable advanced outbound NAT, and click the plus at the bottom of this tab
        to add a NAT mapping for your LAN network.  For this scenario, you will
        want to add a rule for interface WAN, source 192.168.1.0/24, destination
        any, target box blank, and enter a description of your choosing. </para>  
        
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <?dbhtml filename="nat-choosing.html"?>
      <title>Choosing the appropriate NAT for your network</title>
      
      <para>So by now you may be thinking "so what kind of NAT do I need?", to which
      the answer is "it depends."  </para>
      
      <para>For networks with <emphasis role="bold">one public IP</emphasis>, the
      only option is Inbound NAT, since that public IP will be assigned to m0n0wall's
      WAN interface.  </para>
      
      <para>For networks with <emphasis role="bold">multiple public IP addresses</emphasis>,
      the best choice is either 1:1 NAT, or Server and Inbound NAT, or a combination of
      both.  If you have more servers than public IP addresses, you will need to use Server
      and Inbound NAT, or 1:1 NAT combined with Server and Inbound NAT.  If you have sufficient
      public IP addresses for all of your servers, you should use 1:1 NAT for them all.  </para>
      
      <para>Inbound and Server NAT is most suitable when you have more servers than public IP
      addresses.  For example, if you have three servers, one HTTP, one SMTP, and one FTP,
      and have only two public IP addresses, you must use Server and Inbound NAT.  For small
      deployments, this isn't bad to deal with.  As the number of hosts increases, things get
      far more complicated.  You'll end up having to remember things like for public IP address
      1.2.3.4, port 80 goes to server A, port 25 goes to server B, port 21 goes to server C, etc.
      If you can't clearly picture a network in your head while troubleshooting problems, things
      become much more difficult.  With ports going all over the place like this, once you get a
      number of ports forwarded it's extremely difficult to picture the network in your head.
      Given the complexity introduced by such a configuration, we recommend having one public IP
      address per publicly-accessible host.  </para>
      
    </sect1>
        

</chapter>