<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: pptp.xml,v 1.1 2005/07/05 00:43:50 chris Exp $ -->
<chapter id="PPTP">
  <?dbhtml filename="pptp.html"?>

  <title>PPTP</title>

  <remark>This chapter is based on Francisco Artes' m0n0wall-PPTP document,
  used with permission.</remark>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-prehace.html"?>

    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>This chapter is intended to outline several different PPTP VPN type
    setups, it includes a how-to on setting up a <emphasis>Windows
    XP</emphasis> ™ PPTP client to connect to the
    <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis> PPTP VPN server. Later versions of this
    document will include Linux and other clients.</para>

    <para>All Trade Marks ™ are represented in this document, and no intention
    is made that this document, <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis>, or the author
    are in any way related to any of the companies holding these Trade Marks.
    All Trade Marks are copy written by their respective companies.</para>

    <para>The terms firewall and <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis> are used
    synonymously in this chapter. This is mostly because it is easier to say
    and type “firewall”.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-audience.html"?>

    <title>Audience</title>

    <para>You need to have a basic understanding of TCP/IP and subnetting to
    understand this document. The author does make every effort to describe
    the items being discussed, but let’s face it I can only go so far. (And I
    did include pictures, which apparently are each worth 1,000 words. So that
    makes this one HUGE document.)</para>

    <para>If you have comments, questions, or suggestions in regard to this
    document please email <email>falcor@netassassin.com</email>. I will try to
    get back to you as quickly as possible, but please do read this document
    thoroughly before writing. You may also want to check the
    <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis> website for email archives on frequently (or
    even one-time) questions.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-assumptions.html"?>

    <title>Assumptions</title>

    <para>Ok we are going to make several assumptions in this document, if you
    don’t have these assumptions done already you will need to go get them
    done before PPTP will work correctly.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Your firewall is already setup to do basic NAT and you have
        tested this, or at least it is doing what ever kind of routing you
        wanted it to do.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You have configured at least one interface on the firewall so it
        is working and:</para>

        <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <para>The Client Machine(s) can route to (access) one of the
            interfaces of your firewall. Make sure of this. If it is an
            interface that you allow ICMP to access I suggest pinging
            it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You have a client machine running some form of VPN client that
        supports PPTP.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Ok now that we have the basics let’s get started on the firewall
    settings.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-subnetting.html"?>

    <title>Subnetting and VLAN routing</title>

    <para>Ok so this isn’t quite true VLAN routing, but we will (quite
    possibly) be working with a virtual network that doesn’t exist until a
    PPTP connection is made. If you have a better term for this let me know
    and I will change it. We are however dealing with some virtual subnets,
    for instance the “Remote Address Range” will be a /28 and PPTP clients
    will receive a subnet of 255.255.255.255 (ff.ff.ff.ff for all you HEX
    people out there.) Just ignore that and trust in the magic of the PPTP
    Tunnel.</para>

    <para>You can select (as you will see later) to set the “Sever Address”
    and “Remote Address Range” to exist inside of the subnet that you defined
    for the LAN on the firewall. (e.g. IP Address and subnet bit you set for
    the LAN under Interfaces  LAN on the <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis> menu.)
    Our example uses this setup. Pros and Cons? Well the major pro is that the
    firewall will allow traffic from this VLAN to route to the WAN (in most
    cases the Internet.) and it is nice and easy. Con’s, it allows people to
    rout to the WAN if you don’t want this then read the next
    paragraph.</para>

    <para>You can also setup these two options to have an IP range that is
    outside of your LAN designation. E.g. LAN = 192.168.1.1/24 (really the
    192.168.1.0/24 network) and the PPTP “Server Address” and “Remote Address
    Range” are set to 192.168.2.254 and 192.168.2.16/28 respectively. This
    will basically allow those using the PPTP connection to access the LAN,
    but the firewall will not route traffic for them to the WAN connection.
    Opt and WiFi networks will also be isolated depending on how you are
    routing to those networks and if they are in the same network segment
    (subnet) as the LAN.</para>

    <para>Remember, that when you setup a PPTP connection (especially on
    <emphasis>Windows</emphasis>) all network traffic from that workstation is
    going to be sent via the PPTP tunnel.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-setup.html"?>

    <title>Setup of m0n0wall software</title>

    <para>Most people probably skipped right to this point. If you did, it
    should be easy enough with these examples if you do run into something go
    read the parts you skipped you may find the answers there you are looking
    for.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>The first thing we want to do is setup the PPTP server. To do
        this select PPTP from the VPN section of the
        <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis> interface. If you clicked the right
        thing you will have a screen that looks something like <emphasis
        role="strong">Figure 1</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/vpn-pptp.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>The next step is to enable the PPTP server. Click the “Enable
        PPTP server” radio button. (It only gets harder from here.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Now we have to type. (see harder) So enter the “Server Address”
        next. This can be an unused IP on your LAN, or another locally usable
        IP address in a separate subnet. It MUST be in the same networking
        class as the next entry.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Remote Address range. This is going to be the range of 16 IP
        addresses that the server will issue to clients. Notice the /28, it is
        there to remind you there will be 16 hosts. Again, this MUST be in the
        same subnet class as the IP listed above. (Not in the same /28
        though…. If you try to overlap the two the firewall will tell you that
        you made a mistake.)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>In our example we used 192.168.1.254 for the “Server Address” and
    192.168.1.192/28 as the “Remote address range.” Think of the “Sever
    Address” as the default route for the IPs you are going to be issuing to
    the clients. It is also the virtual interface for the PPTP server.</para>

    <para>If you are confused here, or in step 3, please go back and read the
    section named “Subnetting and VLAN routing” as it covered this in more
    detail.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>If you have a RADIUS server of some sort feel free to fill in
        the next few boxes. I don’t so they are blank on this example and
        frankly go outside of the scope of this document anyway.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you are really security conscious, and your client software
        supports it, check the box to require 128-bit encryption.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click “Save” We are all done setting up the server. Now let’s
        setup some users.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-users.html"?>

    <title>PPTP User Setup</title>

    <para>If you have a RADIUS server and you set it up in the previous
    section you can either choose to skip this one, or add users here that
    will be found and used before the PPTP Server sends a request to the
    RADIUS server.</para>

    <para>For the rest of us, this stage is quite important as we need a user
    account to authenticate to the PPTP Server.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Click on “users” under PPTP in the VPN section of the
        <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis> interface.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click the “+” icon and lets fill in some blanks!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter a name in the “Username” box.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter and then re-enter the password for this account. (You
        can’t use special characters at the time of this document, just
        FYI.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click “Save”</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When you get back to the next window you will need to click
        “Apply Settings” NOTE: This will disconnect any active PPTP
        connections. Being as we are just setting this up for the first time,
        and this is our first user, let’s hope there aren’t any to
        disconnect.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If everything went well you should have a screen that looks
        something like <emphasis role="strong">Figure 2</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/vpn-pptp-users.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <para>Now we need to setup a firewall rule so people using the PPTP
    connection can do something with it when they connect.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-firewall.html"?>

    <title>PPTP Firewall Rules</title>

    <para>Yep you need to do this if you want the darn thing to work. But just
    like your LAN rule, you can make this as open or as restrictive as you
    want. Here you can limit the PPTP users to accessing only specific hosts
    on specific ports, or open it all up. We are going to assume you want full
    access for your PPTP users so we are going to setup a firewall rule that
    is exactly like the default LAN rule.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Start by clicking “Rules” under the firewall section of the
        <emphasis>m0n0wall</emphasis> interface.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Next click any of the “+” Icons on the screen so we can add a
        new rule.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/firewall1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <para>As stated we are going to allow all our PPTP users to access all
    parts of the LAN, WAN, etc. If you wish to limit this access then you will
    need to modify things accordingly. I will present one example of such a
    rule after this default section.</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Simply go to the “Interface” section and select PPTP from the
        drop down. In the Description put something meaningful like “Default
        PPTP -&gt; any.”</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click Save</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You will have to Apply the changes on the next screen.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>You are now done setting up the PPTP Server!</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Example of filtered PPTP Rules</title>

      <para>In some cases, most for those people who are granting PPTP access
      to others they do not fully trust, you will want to limit access
      (Specific Allow Rules) or mitigate specific access with Deny Rules. With
      specific allow users would be granted explicit permission to access
      hosts, and sometimes specific ports, and all other traffic is denied.
      The latter would be done if you wanted the PPTP clients to access the
      LAN &amp; WAN but did not want them to access your SAMBA server for
      instance.</para>

      <para>Our example is an allow rule granting permission for people on the
      PPTP network to use SSH on a LAN server with the IP address
      192.168.1.151:</para>

      <para><screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/firewall2.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Save and Apply these rules as needed. Test them all to make sure
      they are working as designed. Most networks are compromised because no
      one checked the ACLs were activated or even working properly.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-windows.html"?>

    <title>Setting up a PPTP Client on <emphasis>Windows
    XP™</emphasis></title>

    <para>This is super easy, and you only have to type one piece of
    information the entire time!</para>

    <para>Start by accessing the Network Connections Panel. (do this however
    you like, I prefer to right click “Network Places” and select
    Properties.)</para>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Click “Create New Connection” in the left hand column of the
        “Network Connections” window.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You are now presented with a Wizard. Click Next to
        continue.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/wizard-new.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Select “Connect to the Network at my Workplace” from the
        menu.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/wizard-type.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Select Virtual Private Network connection from the next
        panel.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/wizard-network.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Name the connection.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Now enter the IP or FQDN of the PPTP Server. (This can be any of
        the configured interfaces.)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/wizard-vpn.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are the system admin you will be asked if you want this
        to be for your use only or for anyone’s use. I suggest you limit it to
        your use only unless you want the VPN network to be made available to
        all user accounts on the workstation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Next you can either just finish or add a shortcut to the
        desktop. You are nearly done!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When you launch the client for the first time (hopefully from
        the icon you asked it to create from the wizard, if not then you will
        need to access the “Network Connections” window again and double click
        your new connection.) you will be asked for a username and password.
        Click connect when you are done with this and if all goes well you
        will connect to the PPTP Server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/wizard-connect.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Testing our PPTP Connection in Windows ™</title>

      <orderedlist continuation="restarts" numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>Start by opening a DOS window. (Command window)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Run ipconfig and you should get something similar to the next
          figure:</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/dos-ipconfig.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>As you hopefully will see you have the settings for your physical
      adapter (in my case I renamed it to ETH0)</para>

      <para>You will also see the PPP Adapter with the name you gave the VPN
      Connection when performing the steps in the last section. It should have
      an IP address that is in the range you defined for the PPTP Server. It
      should also have the subnet of 255.255.255.255 and it will be using
      itself as the default gateway. Just live with it; it is how it
      works.</para>

      <para>For the more advanced who wish to know if things are all working
      right, <emphasis role="strong">Figure 6</emphasis>, displays a full
      ipconfig on the virtual adapter.</para>

      <para><screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/dos-pppconf.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>Now lets try doing something. If you followed the setup for
          this how-to you will have setup full access from the PPTP network to
          the LAN and WAN. If you setup selective rules you will have to test
          specifically what you setup. E.g. if you setup rules to only allow
          SMTP you will need to telnet to the host:25 that you designated in
          the firewall rule. Or write a new rule allowing ICMP to a host that
          will echo a reply back.</para>

          <para>We will be sending a ICMP (Ping) to the firewall’s internal
          interface to test the VPN connection.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In my case the firewall is 192.168.1.1 (please use your
          internal address before writing to me to say pinging 192.168.1.1
          didn’t work on your 10.x.x.x network. Hehe) If done right (assuming
          your firewall isn’t blocking internal ICMP packets) you are good for
          LAN access. (If you are blocking ICMP on the internal interface ping
          some other host on your home network.)</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/dos-ping.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <orderedlist continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>Now lets test beyond the firewall. Ping isn’t so good to use
          here as more and more people are blocking ICMP packets. So we will
          use tracert to check we are 1.) Routing via the PPTP tunnel and 2.)
          That we successful. Of course if you told the firewall to not allow
          WAN access then this step can be skipped.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="screens/pptp/dos-tracert.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>As seen in the last figure, the first hop is the PPTP “Server
      Address” as this is the gateway/interface for the PPTP Network.</para>

      <para>Now check things like HTTP, etc. If you have this much and
      followed the directions you should be able to do everything.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="pptp-notes.html"?>

    <title>Some things I have found not to work over the PPTP
    Connection</title>

    <para>These are more limits in PPTP than other VPN protocols.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>NAT sometimes does not play nice with PPTP. Though m0n0wall
        seems to have this licked, and it works rather well.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Major “Gotcha!” If you are visiting a remote network where the
        network range is the same as the network range on the PPTP Network
        (your LAN network in most cases) then the PPTP tunnel will not work.
        E.g. You are using a WiFi connection in a local coffee shop and the
        network range it has put you in is 192.168.1.0/24. You try to connect
        to your home network via PPTP, but your home also uses 192.168.1.0/24.
        The tunnel/authentication to the PPTP server will happen, but no
        traffic will go across that tunnel due to the “confusion” in the
        TCP/IP stack on your workstation. To get around this use some odd
        network range at home. E.x. 192.168.88.0/24. Most people use 10.0.0.1
        and 192.168.1.0 so try to set your home network differently. This will
        also help when you setup IPSEC tunnels between your house and say your
        friend’s house.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Some ISP's use unreasonably short DHCP lease times, like one
        hour. If the PPTP client machine gets a short lease from DHCP, it will
        lose internet connectivity after the lease expires. This is because
        all network traffic, including your DHCP renewal requests, are going
        across the VPN. Since it can't hit the local DHCP server through the
        VPN, when the lease expires your machine will release its IP address.
        This causes the loss of all connectivity. You have to disconnect from
        the PPTP (if it doesn't disconnect itself), renew your IP address, and
        reconnect. This is common on Windows hosts, and likely other OS's as
        well. If this happens, contact the administrator of your DHCP server
        (likely the client machine's ISP) and get the lease time
        lengthened.</para>

        <para>The author has seen this situation numerous times, and in every
        case, the ISP was willing to help and resolved the problem. Your
        mileage may vary.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>UPnP packets from your LAN do not make it to the PPTP network.
        This is more than likely because the current version of m0n0wall does
        not support UPnP. (In English: those of use having dreams of accessing
        our ReplayTV ™ or other media devices that use UPnP can dream of other
        things for now. It is actually more secure to not have UPnP on a
        firewall, but some people overlook that so they can use voice chat
        software and DVRs.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Network Neighborhood in Windows does not work over PPTP
        connections because broadcasts are not forwarded across the PPTP
        connection.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>I haven’t really beaten the PPTP tunnel that much yet, so if you
    find more items that don’t seem to work right let me know and I will add
    them here so people don’t go crazy trying to figure out something that
    just won’t work. ;)</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>