<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: ref.xml,v 1.1 2005/07/05 00:43:50 chris Exp $ -->
<appendix>
  <?dbhtml filename="ref.html"?>

  <title>Reference</title>

  <sect1 id="Ref.IP">
    <?dbhtml filename="ref-ip.html"?>

    <title>IP Basics</title>

    <para>You can change the hostname and domain used by your firewall in the
    <link linkend="Config.System.General">General Setup</link> screen.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ref-filtering.html"?>

    <title>IP Filtering</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ref-nat.html"?>

    <title>NAT</title>

    <para>NAT (Network Address Translation) permits you to use private IP
    address space on your LAN while still being able to access the
    internet.</para>

    <para>There are two main types of NAT in m0n0wall, inbound, and
    1:1.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ref-shaping.html"?>

    <title>Traffic Shaping</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Ref.DNS">
    <?dbhtml filename="ref-dns.html"?>

    <title>DNS</title>

    <para>You can change the DNS servers used by your firewall in the <link
    linkend="Config.System.General">General Setup</link> screen.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="ref-encryption.html"?>

    <title>Encryption (PPTP/IPsec)</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Ref.Logging">
    <?dbhtml filename="ref-logging.html"?>

    <title>Logging (syslog)</title>

    <para></para>

    <para>It is recommended that you log your m0n0wall to a remote syslog
    server for diagnostics and forensic purposes. There are a number of free
    tools receive and store syslog messages for you on Windows, Mac, and Unix
    based systems. These software packages also offer additional features such
    as automatically sending pages, emails or SMS messages as well as running
    software or commands based on the messages that are received.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>Log messages include a timestamp of when the event ocurred. The
      system time on the firewall is synchronized to an NTP (Network Time
      Protocol) server. You can change the NTP server and related parameters
      in the <link linkend="Config.System.General">General Setup</link>
      screen.</para>
    </tip>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Unix-based tools</emphasis></para>

    <para>The syslog daemon built into virtually every Unix-like system can be
    configured to accept log messages from remote hosts. Check documentation
    specific to your OS on how to configure syslogd to accept messages from
    remote hosts.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Other Unix Tools</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"> <ulink
    url="http://www.balabit.com/products/syslog_ng/">syslog-ng</ulink>
    </emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"> <ulink
    url="http://coombs.anu.edu.au/~avalon/nsyslog.html">nsyslog</ulink>
    </emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows-based tools</emphasis></para>

    <para>There are several free and commercial tools available on Windows to
    enable your system to accept syslog messages from hosts on your
    network.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Kiwi Syslog</emphasis></para>

    <para>One of my favorites on Windows is Kiwi Syslog. There is a version
    with "basic" features that is free, and a more advanced version with $49
    registration. Even if you are just looking for a free tool, the basic
    version has as many if not more features than any other free package on
    this list. <ulink
    url="http://www.kiwi-enterprises.com/">http://www.kiwi-enterprises.com/
    </ulink></para>

    <para>3Com offers a couple of free utilities on <ulink
    url="http://support.3com.com/software/utilities_for_windows_32_bit.htm">this
    page.</ulink> 3CSyslog is a GUI tool best used on a temporary or as-needed
    basis only. To collect logs using a service that will be running at all
    times, whether or not anyone is logged into the machine, try
    wsyslogd.</para>

    <para>Several more for Windows and a couple for Mac listed on <ulink
    url="http://www.practicallynetworked.com/support/syslog.htm">this
    site.</ulink></para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>