<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting.html"?>

  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>This chapter outlines some of the more common problems you may
  experience when using m0n0wall, and how to troubleshoot and resolve
  them.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Interfaces are not detected</title>

    <para>First check your BIOS settings for a "Plug and Play OS" or "OS"
    setting. For "Plug and Play OS", set it to "no" or "disable". If there is
    an "OS" setting, typically you can and should set it to "other". This most
    always fixes the problem.</para>

    <para>If that doesn't resolve it, try to upgrade your system BIOS.</para>

    <para>Resetting the BIOS to default settings might help. There have been
    instances in the past where this has resolved this problem, likely due to
    some strange BIOS setup from past use of the hardware.</para>

    <para>Occasionally other hardware like sound cards, and similar, can
    prevent some or all of your cards from being detected. Try removing any
    cards in the system that aren't required, and disabling any unused
    hardware (USB, parallel port, serial ports, any onboard sound, etc.) in
    the system BIOS.</para>

    <para>Most all Ethernet cards are supported by m0n0wall, but if you still
    cannot see the network cards, ensure they are supported.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-immediate-replacement.html"?>

    <title>After replacing my current firewall with m0n0wall using the same
    public IP, m0n0wall cannot get an Internet connection.</title>

    <para>This same problem can affect new 1:1 and Server NAT
    configurations.</para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Cause</title>

      <para>This is typically caused by the router outside of your m0n0wall
      having the MAC address of your previous firewall still in its ARP table.
      Cisco routers, for example, will cache this for four hours by default.
      Many other routers are similar.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <bridgehead>Solution</bridgehead>

    <para>Clear the ARP cache on your router. If you don't have access to the
    command interface of the router, or don't know how to clear the ARP cache,
    power cycling the router should achieve the same result.</para>

    <para>Alternatively, you could fill in the MAC address of the WAN
    interface of your previous firewall in m0n0wall's WAN interface
    screen.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Troubleshooting.no.link.light">
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-nolinklight.html"?>

    <title>No Link Light</title>

    <para>If you do not have a link light on your network interfaces, they are
    not up and will not be able to communicate with the network. Your LAN and
    WAN interfaces both must have link lights.</para>

    <para>If you do not have a link light on one of your network interfaces,
    there are a few potential causes and things to check.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ensure the network cable is snugly plugged in on both ends.
        Unplug and replug the cable to ensure it is properly seated.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Try a different cable.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure you are using the appropriate type of cable.</para>

        <para>There are two types of standard Ethernet patch cables, straight
        and crossover.</para>

        <bridgehead>Straight cables</bridgehead>

        <para>are used to attach devices like computers, routers (ones like
        Cisco, not counting most DSL and cable routers/modems), servers,
        printers, firewalls, and other devices with Ethernet cards into a hub
        or switch.</para>

        <bridgehead>Crossover cables</bridgehead>

        <para>are used to connect one hub or switch to another hub or switch,
        or connect a PC directly to another PC, or a firewall directly to a
        PC, etc.</para>

        <para>Make sure you are using the appropriate cable type for your
        situation. If you are unsure of which cable is required and do not get
        a link light with a straight cable, try a crossover cable.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If none of the above apply and you still are not getting a link
    light, verify functionality of both pieces of equipment by trying other
    devices. If you cannot get a link light on a network device no matter what
    you plug it into with any kind of cable, the device has a bad Ethernet
    port.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Cannot.Access.webGUI">
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-nowebgui.html"?>

    <title>Cannot Access webGUI</title>

    <para>If you cannot access the webGUI after following this guide, verify
    the following.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Check the link lights on the network ports on the WRAP.
        Connected interfaces must have a link light or they will not work. If
        you do not have a link light, check the "no link light"
        troubleshooting section of this guide. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check to make sure you have the interfaces plugged in properly.
        Remember on the WRAP the NIC closest to the power supply must be
        connected to your LAN hub or switch. On the three NIC models, the
        middle interface is WAN, and on the two NIC models, the interface
        closest to the serial port is WAN. The WAN port must be plugged into
        your Internet connection (cable or DSL modem, router, etc.). </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Try to ping the LAN IP of m0n0wall. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check the IP configuration of the machine you are using. Its IP
        address must be within the same subnet as your m0n0wall's LAN
        interface, and must be using the same subnet mask. </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-nointernetfromlan.html"?>

    <title>Cannot Access Internet from LAN after WAN Configuration</title>

    <para>The following diagram provides an overview of troubleshooting this
    issue. Each step is numbered with the section of this document that
    addresses troubleshooting this particular issue.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="flowcharts/no-internet-from-LAN.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <sect2>
      <title>Ping m0n0wall LAN IP</title>

      <para>Bring up a command prompt on your machine, type in 'ping
      192.168.1.1' and press Enter.</para>

      <para>A successful ping will look like the following.</para>

      <literallayout class="monospaced">
C:\&gt;ping 192.168.1.1

Pinging 192.168.1.1 with 32 bytes of data:

Reply from 192.168.1.1: bytes=32 time&lt;1ms TTL=64
Reply from 192.168.1.1: bytes=32 time&lt;1ms TTL=64
Reply from 192.168.1.1: bytes=32 time&lt;1ms TTL=64
Reply from 192.168.1.1: bytes=32 time&lt;1ms TTL=64

Ping statistics for 192.168.1.1:
    Packets: Sent = 4, Received = 4, Lost = 0 (0% loss),
Approximate round trip times in milli-seconds:
    Minimum = 0ms, Maximum = 0ms, Average = 0ms
        </literallayout>

      <para>An unsuccessful ping will look like this.</para>

      <literallayout class="monospaced">
C:\&gt;ping 192.168.1.1

Pinging 192.168.1.1 with 32 bytes of data:

Request timed out.
Request timed out.
Request timed out.
Request timed out.

Ping statistics for 192.168.1.1:
    Packets: Sent = 4, Received = 0, Lost = 4 (100% loss),
        </literallayout>

      <para>See <link linkend="Cannot.Access.webGUI">Cannot Access
      webGUI</link> as if you cannot ping, you won't be able to get into the
      webGUI either.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="check.WAN.IP">
      <title>Check m0n0wall's WAN IP</title>

      <para>Go to the Status -&gt; Interfaces page and look under the WAN
      interface. It must show status as up, and have a valid IP address,
      subnet mask, and gateway.</para>

      <para>If the status shows as "down", check for a link light. See <link
      linkend="no.link.light">No Link Light</link> if you do not have a link
      light on your WAN NIC.</para>

      <para>If you have a dynamic IP connection like DHCP, PPPoE, or anything
      but static, and show a 0.0.0.0 IP, you are not getting a lease from your
      ISP. Check your WAN configuration page to make sure the appropriate
      settings are entered correctly (like username/password if applicable,
      etc.).</para>

      <para>If you see a WAN IP address on the Status -&gt; Interfaces page,
      make note of it as you will use it in the next step.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Cannot get IP address on dynamic IP connection</title>

        <para>If all settings are correct and you still cannot get a lease and
        have a DSL or cable modem, try powering off the modem for several
        seconds and powering it back on. Then go to the WAN interface page,
        and without saving any changes, click the Save button (or just power
        cycle m0n0wall if you prefer). Then check the Status -&gt; Interfaces
        page again to see if you now have an IP address.</para>

        <para>If you still don't have an IP and previously had some other
        router, firewall, or PC connected to this Internet connection, your
        ISP may be restricting you to only using the MAC address of the
        previous device. The easiest thing to do in these situations is to get
        the MAC address off the device that was formerly connected and enter
        it in the "MAC address" box under "General configuration" on the WAN
        page in the m0n0wall webGUI. On most routers, you can find the MAC
        address on a sticker on the device. On Windows PC's, you can get the
        MAC address by running "ipconfig/all" from a command prompt. On BSD
        and Linux machines, you can get the MAC address by running
        'ifconfig'.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Ping m0n0wall's WAN IP</title>

      <para>On the Status -&gt; Interfaces page, make note of the WAN IP
      address. On the client machine you are using, try to ping that IP
      address.</para>

      <para>If the ping is not successful, check the default gateway IP
      address on the client machine. Run 'ipconfig/all' from a command prompt
      if using Windows to check this. It must be set to m0n0wall's LAN IP
      (192.168.1.1 by default).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Ping m0n0wall's WAN's gateway IP</title>

      <para>On the Status -&gt; Interfaces page, make note of m0n0wall's WAN
      default gateway IP. Try to ping it from your client machine.</para>

      <para>If the pings time out, double check your WAN setup. If things fail
      at this stage, you most likely failed the earlier <link
      linkend="check.WAN.IP"> Check WAN IP</link> step as well.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Ping an IP address on the Internet</title>

      <para>From the client machine, ping something on the Internet that
      responds to pings, like 216.135.66.19.</para>

      <para>If this fails but all previous steps were successful, your ISP is
      not letting you out onto the Internet for some reason. At this point,
      you will need to contact your ISP's technical support. Your ISP could
      potentially be blocking pings though (not likely), so your pings could
      time out while your Internet connection still functions (mostly)
      properly.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Ping a DNS name that responds to pings</title>

      <para>Ping a DNS name that responds to pings from the client machine,
      like google.com.</para>

      <para>You should see responses to your pings. If you receive a "could
      not find host" message, you have a DNS issue. See the Troubleshooting
      DNS section.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-firewall-rules.html"?>

    <title>Troubleshooting Firewall Rules</title>

    <para>First remember rules are processed top down, and the first match is
    the only rule that applies.</para>

    <para>Secondly, remember to check your logs on the Diagnostics -&gt; Logs,
    Firewall tab. This will show you what is getting dropped due to the
    default deny all rule. When troubleshooting rules, it can be helpful to
    enable logging on the rules in question at least temporarily. Remember
    m0n0wall has limited local logging space, so don't enable too much on a
    long term basis.</para>

    <para>Remember if you need to permit services from the Internet into any
    private IP space, you need to configure NAT as well as firewall rules, and
    we recommend using the "auto add firewall rule" when adding NAT
    entries.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Reading raw IPFilter logs</title>

      <para>If all else fails and you need to determine exactly which rule is
      dropping the traffic, go to status.php on your m0n0wall to the "last 50
      filter log entries" section. Find the log line applying to the traffic
      in question, and make note of the rule number. The rule number is
      denoted by an @ followed by a number, then a colon, then another number,
      for example @0:18. The 0 indicates the first group, and the 18 indicates
      rule number 18 in group 0.</para>

      <para>Then go up to the output of "ipfstat -nio" and find the rule in
      question. Anything without a group number at the end of the rule is the
      0 group. @1:1 would indicate the first rule with "group 100" at the end
      of the rule. @2:1 would be the first rule with "group 200" at the end of
      the rule, and so on. Finding the exact rule, since some rules are added
      by the back end of m0n0wall and not visible on the rules page, may make
      troubleshooting easier.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-bridging.html"?>

    <title>Troubleshooting Bridging</title>

    <para>In order to support bridging, the network cards you are using must
    support promiscuous mode. Not all do. Some people have reported problems
    with Realtek chipsets not supporting promiscuous mode. To determine if
    your NIC does, see its documentation.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-bridging.html"?>

    <title>Troubleshooting IPsec Site to Site VPN</title>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Check the SAD</title>

      <para>Check the Security Association Database (SAD) under Diagnostics.
      You need to have an entry here for the connection. If you do not, you
      don't have something configured properly.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <bridgehead>Verify Suitable IP Subnets</bridgehead>

    <para>First make sure the two subnets you are trying to connect don't lie
    within the same address space. i.e. if both sides are 192.168.1.0/24, the
    connection will not work. Same goes if one side is 192.168.0.0/16 and the
    other is 192.168.1.0/24, or similar, the latter lies in the subnet of the
    former.</para>

    <para>If they do lie within the same address space, you'll need to change
    one side or the other. There is no way to set up a site to site IPsec VPN
    with any product when this is the case.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <?dbhtml filename="troubleshooting-freeze.html"?>

    <title>Troubleshooting Solid Freezes</title>

    <para>Certain conditions can cause your m0n0wall to freeze solid
    periodically. The amount of time between freezes typically varies, and can
    be anywhere from a few hours to a few days.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Shared IRQ's</title>

      <para>The first thing to check is whether you have any shared IRQ's.
      This seems to be the most common cause. If you have recently rebooted
      your m0n0wall, you should be able to see the boot messages under
      Diagnostics -&gt; Logs, on the System tab. Otherwise you can go to
      /exec.php on your m0n0wall and run 'dmesg'. Look through the boot
      messages and make note of everything you see being shown with an IRQ.
      This includes your NIC's as well as other devices like serial and
      parallel ports, etc. An example of some dmesg output follows.</para>

      <literallayout class="monospaced">
sis0: &lt;NatSemi DP83815 10/100BaseTX&gt; port 0xe000-0xe0ff mem 0xa0001000-0xa0001fff irq 11 at device 18.0 on pci0
sis1: &lt;NatSemi DP83815 10/100BaseTX&gt; port 0xe100-0xe1ff mem 0xa0002000-0xa0002fff irq 5 at device 19.0 on pci0
sis2: &lt;NatSemi DP83815 10/100BaseTX&gt; port 0xe200-0xe2ff mem 0xa0003000-0xa0003fff irq 9 at device 20.0 on pci0
            </literallayout>

      <para>The above example shows three NIC's with IRQ's 11, 5, and
      9.</para>

      <para>If you note any two devices using a single IRQ, you may need to
      try other PCI slots, if possible, remove unused cards (like sound
      cards), and disable unused devices in the BIOS (serial ports, parallel
      ports, etc.).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>BIOS Version and Settings</title>

      <para>You might want to try resetting your BIOS configuration to factory
      defaults, and then disabling any Plug and Play OS settings. Also check
      that your BIOS is updated to the latest revision.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Hardware Issues</title>

      <para>Use hardware diagnostic utilities to ensure your RAM and system in
      general are functioning properly. The <ulink
      url="http://ultimatebootcd.com/">Ultimate Boot CD</ulink> has several
      utilities for testing CPU and memory.</para>

      <para>Hardware overheating is another common cause. This issue has been
      noted on WRAP hardware especially when using miniPCI cards. It's also
      possible and has happened with any type of hardware.</para>

      <para>If nothing else, it may just be hardware or a combination of
      hardware that doesn't play nicely with FreeBSD. You may want to try
      different NIC's or a different system. This especially seems to be a
      problem with some old AMD K5 and K6 systems, though some work
      fine.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>