<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="webgui.html"?>

  <title>Initial webGUI Configuration</title>

    <para>Now that we have the client machines configured appropriately, the
    interfaces assigned and LAN IP address configured, and the m0n0wall has
    rebooted with its new configuration, we will log into the webGUI and finish
    the configuration.</para>
    
    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="webgui-loggingin.html"?>
        <title>Logging into the webGUI</title>
    
        <para>Open your web browser and go to http://192.168.1.1 (if you changed
        your LAN IP address in the console setup, replace 192.168.1.1 with your LAN IP
        throughout the remainder of this documentation).  </para>
    
        <para>You will be prompted for a username and password.  Enter username admin and
        password mono.  You are now logged into the webGUI.</para>
    
        <mediaobject>
           <imageobject>
             <imagedata fileref="screens/webgui/firstscreen.png" />
           </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="webgui-general.html"?>
        <title>webGUI System -> General Setup screen</title>
        
        <para>First click "General Setup".  </para>
        
        <mediaobject>
           <imageobject>
             <imagedata fileref="screens/webgui/generalsetup.png" />
           </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hostname and Domain</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>If you wish to change the hostname and domain of your m0n0wall, you
        can do so in the first two boxes on this screen.  If you use m0n0wall as
        your DNS server, this name will resolve to your LAN IP address.  i.e. you
        can access your webGUI using http://m0n0wall.local or whatever you set
        the hostname and domain to be. </para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DNS Servers</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>If you have a static IP from your ISP, you need to enter the IP
        addresses of your ISP's DNS servers in these two boxes.  Use one IP address
        per box.  If you get your IP address from your ISP via DHCP, leave these
        boxes blank.  If you want to use DNS servers on your LAN, enter their IP
        addresses here.  You can only use one DNS server by filling in the top
        box and leaving the bottom one blank.</para>
        
        <para>If your ISP uses DHCP and you wish to use the DNS servers the ISP's
        DHCP server provides, leave the "Allow DNS server list to be overridden by
        DHCP/PPP on WAN" box checked.  If you are using DHCP on the WAN and wish
        to use DNS servers other than the ones provided by your ISP, uncheck this
        box.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Username and Password</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>If you wish to change the username from the default "admin", change
        the username box appropriately.</para>
        
        <para>It is important that you change your password from the default
        "mono" by typing in a password of your choosing in the password field and
        typing it again to confirm in the second field.  </para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">webGUI protocol and port</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>Here you should change the protocol from HTTP to HTTPS so your
        username and password and configuration details are encrypted while in
        transit over your LAN.</para>
        
        <para>If you want to make it a little more difficult to find your webGUI
        logon page, change the port number here.  Just remember you will have to
        put that port number in the URL when logging into the webGUI.  For example,
        if you set this port to 5555, and switch to HTTPS, you will have to use
        https://192.168.1.1:5555 to access the webGUI.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Time Zone</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>Select your time zone from this drop down box.  This includes all
        of the time zones from FreeBSD.  I am in Louisville, Kentucky, USA, which
        has its own entry under America/Louisville that I will select.  You can
        likely find a city in the same time zone, or at least find the name of
        your time zone.</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Time Update Interval</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>m0n0wall has a NTP client built in that by default will synchronize
        its time to a NTP server every 300 minutes (5 hours).  To change the
        frequency of this update, change this box.  Enter 0 to disable NTP clock
        synchronization (not recommended).</para>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">NTP Time Server</emphasis></para>
        
        <para>This specifies which NTP server m0n0wall will use to synchronize its
        time.  You can leave it at pool.ntp.org unless you have a reason to change
        it.  You might want to change this, for example, to synchronize to a
        central NTP server on your LAN.</para>
        
        <para>Now review all of your changes on this screen, and when you are
        satisfied with them, click Save.  You'll see notification that the
        changes were applied successfully. </para>
        
        
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="webgui-configurewan.html"?>
        <title>Configuring your WAN interface</title>

        <para>Now we will configure your WAN interface.  At this point, you will
        need some information from your ISP.  The WAN connection types available
        are DHCP, static IP, PPPoE, PPTP, and BigPond.  Chances are you will be
        using DHCP, static IP, or PPPoE.  </para>
        
        <sect2>
            <title>WAN configuration screen</title>
            
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="screens/webgui/wan.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
            <title>Type</title>
            
            <para>In the Type drop down box, you have five choices.  Choose
            accordingly for the information you gathered earlier, and fill
            in any necessary information for your connection type.</para>
            
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
            <title>General configuration options</title>
            
            <para>Under "General configuration" on this screen, you can change
            the MAC address of the WAN interface and change the MTU.</para>
            
            <para><emphasis role="bold">MAC address</emphasis></para>
            
            <para>Some ISP's keep the MAC address of the device you have connected
            to their network, and only allow that device access.  There is typically
            a process to register a new device, though sometimes that may require
            contacting the ISP.  To avoid this, you can enter the MAC address of
            the network card you previously used on your broadband connection to
            make your ISP think you still have the same device connected.</para>
            
            <para><emphasis role="bold">MTU</emphasis></para>
            
            <para>Unless you have a very good reason for changing it, leave the
            MTU alone.</para>
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
            <title>Block private networks</title>
            
            <para>Unless your WAN subnet lies in private IP address
            space, leave this box checked.  It protects you from
            some IP spoofing attempts.</para>
            
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
            <title>Save and Apply Changes</title>
            
            <para>Now click Save at the bottom of the WAN page.  Your changes
            will immediately take effect, and you should immediately be able to
            browse the internet from your LAN.  If you cannot, see the troubleshooting
            section.</para>
            
        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <?dbhtml filename="webgui-configured.html"?>
        <title>What next?</title>
        
        <para>So you now have m0n0wall configured and working - now what next?</para>
        
        <sect2>
          <title>m0n0wall Announcements List</title>
          
        <para>If you are running m0n0wall, we strongly suggest subscribing to the
        announcements mailing list by sending a blank email to
        &lt;m0n0wall-announce-subscribe@lists.m0n0.ch&gt;.  This is a very low volume
        list that can only be posted to by Manuel Kasper.  It might get 10 messages
        a year.  It's <emphasis role="bold">important to subscribe</emphasis> so you
        are kept up to date on any new releases, and will know if any security issues
        are discovered.</para>
        
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
          <title>m0n0wall Documentation Announcements List</title>
        
        <para>You might also wish to subscribe to the documentation updates list if you
        want to keep up to date on major changes to the m0n0wall documentation.  Send a
        blank email to &lt;m0n0wall-doc-announce-subscribe@lists.m0n0.ch&gt; to subscribe.
        This list can only be posted to by Chris Buechler, and is very low volume with
        typically less than 10 messages per year.  </para>
        
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
          <title>Explore the Possibilities</title>
          
          <para>m0n0wall is capable of much more than the basic two interface LAN/WAN
          setup you now have running.  Peruse the <ulink url="http://doc.m0n0.ch/handbook/">
            m0n0wall Handbook</ulink> for information on
          implementing more of m0n0wall's capabilities.</para>
          
        </sect2>
        
    </sect1>
</chapter>